If you want to talk about quantum channels in the most
generality, they are actually completely positive
space-preserving maps, and they are really complicated, even
to write down the definition.
Well, maybe not to write down the definition,
but to intuitively--
they're really quite difficult to understand.
And if you want to learn about them,
you can take the follow up to this course,
which is 8371, or 18436.
But today, we'll tell you the simplest kind
of quantum channel, which is all the kind, which is--
I mean, we can do everything we want to in this course
with that kind of channel.
So what is a quantum channel?
So what we're going to do is we're
going to express a quantum channel as a mixture
of simple channels.
Probabilistic mixture simple channels.
So that's not always true, but let's do the easiest one first,
what we'll call the dephasing channel.
So let's say, with probability 1 minus p, you do nothing.
Probability p, apply sigma z.
So let's put a quantum state into the depolarizing channel.
So suppose you put in alpha 0 plus beta 1.
You get out a mixture.
You get out 1 minus p, probability alpha 0,
plus beta 1.
And with p probability, you get out alpha 0 minus beta 1.
And from last time's lecture, we know
this can be expressed as a density matrix,
so the density matrix is 1 minus p alpha 0 plus beta 1, alpha 0
plus beta 1 plus p.
Same thing with minus signs.
And that's 1 minus p, alpha squared.
Let's assume alpha and beta are real, because--
alpha beta, alpha beta, beta squared.
Yeah.
Because otherwise, we get a whole bunch
of complex conjugates, which I don't want to mess up.
Now, down here, you get alpha 0 minus beta 1.
That gives you alpha squared minus alpha beta
minus alpha beta, beta squared is equal to--
well, 1 minus p alpha squared plus alpha squared.
p alpha squared is just alpha squared.
And the same thing for beta squared.
And you have 1 minus 2p alpha beta and--
OK, I'm going to rewrite that down here.
Alpha squared, 1 minus 2p alpha beta, 1 minus 2p alpha beta,
beta squared.
And the density matrix we put in was alpha squared, alpha beta,
alpha beta, beta squared.
So the depolarizing channel, you can see from this example,
and this example is--
well, this is as general as possible,
really, except you also should check that it works
with alpha and beta complex.
So what the depolarizing channel does
is it multiplies the alpha diagonal elements
of the density matrix--
sorry, the dephasing channel.
The dephasing multiplies the alpha diagonal elements
of the density matrix by some constant.