So let me tell you the proof of this.
So the idea of Gottesman-Knill is we cannot afford to write
down the state of the wave vector.
But we can maintain it--
we can think about the state just in terms of the stabilizer
generators.
So the idea is you keep track of the stabilizers,
more precisely the stabilizer generators.
OK, so let's see what this looks like.
So initially, the state is just n copies of the 0 state.
So I can think of it as a one-dimensional stabilizer
subspace.
So remind me, what are the polys that stabilize this subspace?
Yeah.
Say that again, z what?
[INAUDIBLE]
Right, so a z on each individual qubit.
So the stabilizer subgroup you can think of as
generated by z1, z2, through zn.
Right?
Because if the plus-1 eigenstate of zi,
that means that the i-th qubit must
be in the [INAUDIBLE] 0 state.
And it's crucial I keep track of the generators
here, right, because there are 2 to the n possible products
of these.
I cannot write down all of those.
But that would be wasteful.
You know, I just need to write down the generators,
and then I know the whole space.
And I'm going to write these in terms of operators,
but hopefully you should see that I can just as well do it
in terms of the f2 linear algebra perspective.
Like, I could think of these as vectors in f2 to the 2n,
and it's really just saying the same thing.
So when I perform a unitary, then I'm
going to map this to uz1, u-dagger through uzn, u-dagger.
So I now need to update these stabilizers.
But I can do this with f2 linear algebra,
right, because this unitary just corresponds
to multiplying by some symplectic matrix
and maybe performing a phase.
And you might worry big Clifford is hard to describe,
but the big Clifford I can always break up into--
in fact, it's given to me as a circuit, right.
And the circuit is just a sequence
of one and two cubic gates--
Hadamards, phase gates, controlled-NOT.
And so, for each one of those it's
a very simple calculation to update these stabilizers.
And so, as I go through the circuit,
I just track my n different stabilizers as they evolve.
OK?
So now I've done my circuit.
I have a pure state at the end, and it remains only
to simulate measurement.
So measurement is the tricky part.
Now, because I can kind of rotate one stabilizer
into any other one, it suffices to measure z1.
And because I can do adaptive measurements,
let's say I want to measure all the qubits-- like I measure z1,
then z2, then da-da-da, zn--
that still fits within this adaptive--
where'd I write it?
Up here, this adaptive framework.
Right, I could do z1 and then swap qubits 1 and 2, and then
measure z1 again, then swap qubits 1 and 3 and measure z1
again.
So if I can just measure z1, I can basically
measure all the qubits in the computational basis
or whatever subset I feel like.
OK, so how do I measure z1?
So there's a few cases here.
Suppose that z1 is contained in s.
Then what happens with my measurement?
What outcome will I get?
Or will it be random?
So I have a state which is stabilized by s, right.
So that means that if I act on the state with anything of s,
I get back the state itself.
z1 is in s, and I'm measuring z1.
So what is the outcome of that measurement going to be?
What's that?
Plus 1, right.
My state is a plus-1 eigenspace of everything of s,
including z1.
So if I'm in an eigenstate and I measure,
I get a deterministic answer.
So if z1 is in s, outcome is plus 1.
Great.
Now, not quite done.
I'm doing this adaptively, right.
I'm going to make a measurement and then do some more unitary,
then another measurement.
So I have to worry about the post-measurement state.
So how does the state change after the measurement?
Getting a-- shaking a head.
It doesn't change because--?
Right, because it's an eigenstate.
And so when I get an eigenstate, I
have a deterministic answer and no change.
So outcome plus 1, state unchanged.
Great.
So now there's a different case, which
will give me outcome minus 1, state unchanged.
What is the condition that would give rise to this outcome?
Yeah?
Exactly.
So if I just say, if minus z1 is in the stabilizer,
then the outcome is--
that it's the other way around.
Then I deterministically get outcome minus 1.
Because I'm stabilized by minus z1
means that I'm a plus-1 eigenstate of that operator
or a minus-1 eigenstate of z1.
OK, now the next case is at plus or minus z1
is not contained in s.
So as an aside, I claim that s here is equal to n of s.
And this is not always true.
In general, n of s can be bigger than s.
But I claim that if you have a one-dimensional stabilizer
subspace, then s is equal to n of s.
So there is a few reasons for this.
One of them, remember that if s has size 2 to the k,
then n of s has size--
sorry, 2 to the n minus k, then n of s
has size 2 to the n of s, 2 to the n plus k.
That's something we derived before.
So if k is 0, then these have the same size.
But n of s contains s.
And they have the same size, so they must be the same set.
Another argument for this is that if you
look at the things that are in n of s, but not s,
these are things which cause non-trivial changes,
but leave you within the subspace.
But if you're subspace is one-dimensional,
then there are no operators that will map you
to a different state.
There are no other states to map you to, right.
All you can do is change the phase.
So there can be nothing in n of s that that's outside of s,
except for minus identities.
So what that means is that plus or minus z1 is also not
in n of s, which means there exists--
so let's say that s, we've been tracking the generators,
and they're si through sn minus k.
That means that there exists some j, such that z1 and sj
anti-commute.
So at least one, right.
That's what it means to not be in the normalizer.
It means you don't commute with all of them, i.e.
you anti-commute with at least one of them, maybe more.
So what I would like to do is get to the situation
where z1 only anti-commutes with one of them, OK.
So how am I going to do this?
So first, reorder so that instead of it just being sum
sj, it's s1, so that z1,s1 is equal to minus s1,z1.
I mean, I have n things in some arbitrary order.
Oh, I'm sorry.
I wrote s1 through sn minus k.
That should have been just sn, right,
because I have n stabilizer generators--
because I have one-dimensional state.
So I don't care about the order of the generators.
So let's just call the one that I know I anti-commute with s1.
Now there might be more that I anti-commute with.
So suppose there exists some other j, more than one,
such that z1 and sj anti-commute.
I only want z1 to anti-commute with one of the generators,
not with all of them, or not with many of them.
So what can I do about this?
Well I have a few freedom in my choices of generator.
So first of all, I mean, I can obviously reorder them.
That's what I just did.
But I can also multiply them by each other,
and I will still get a valid set of generators.
So it's like if I take a linearly independent set
of vectors and I add one vector to another one,
still the linearly independent, still generates the same set.
So what I can do is replace sj with s1 times sj, OK.
They still generate the same set because I'm just
taking all products of them.
And so anytime I would have used sj prime, I just use these two.
And it definitely is--
any product involving sj-prime will still
be a product involving s1 and sj.
And vice versa, any product involving sj,
I could write in terms of sj-prime.
And now, I claim that if z1 anti-commutes
with both s1 and sj, then it will commute with sj-prime.
So now z1, sj-prime is equal to sj-prime, z1
because when I move sj-prime past it,
it's like I'm moving s1 and sj.
Each one of them will pick up a minus-1.
Overall, I'll pick up a plus-1.
OK?
So now I can replace s--
so I can have new generators, s1 through sn,
such that only s1 anti-commutes with z1.
And so what that means is, I don't have to worry about all
of the other stabilizer generators.
When I measure z1, it's going to mess up
the stabilizers somehow, right.
I can't always say the state doesn't change.
The state's going to change.
But it's not going to be total chaos.
It's not going to change all the stabilizers.
It commutes with now s2 through sn,
so it will not change any of those.
It will only change s1.
So that's going to make my life a lot easier.
So now I could just ignore s2 through sn.
Let's just focus in on s1 and see what z1 does here.
OK?
Furthermore, we can now see a little bit about s1.
So suppose I know that s1 anti-commutes with z1.
What can I say about s1 as a poly?
Yeah.
Say that again.
A little bit louder.
Orthogonal.
Right, so in terms of f2, we can say
that it has inner product 1 with this corresponding vector.
But let's just think about s1 as like a poly
on the first qubit, a poly on the second qubit,
a poly on the third qubit, et cetera.
What can I say about those polys?
Like, what can I say about the poly on the second qubit
or on the first qubit?
So I can write, you know, s1 is equal to--
you know, what goes in the first qubit,
second qubit, third qubit?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Right, so the first qubit has to be either x or y.
So let me write x1 or y1 times something else--
let's call it g--
which is only on qubits 2 through n.
And furthermore, all the other s2 through sn--
similar logic-- means that these are i or z1 times
something, operator on qubits 2 through n.
So now what's going to happen when I make this measurement?
To give a sense of it, suppose that this s1 was just x1.
Then what happens is, when I measure z1,
I get a random plus-minus 1 outcome.
Corresponding to the outcome, I'm
going to add a new generator.
So I'm going to add plus or minus z1
to the set of stabilizers.
And I'm going to just discard s1.
So if this was, for example, just poly-x, x1, and I measure
in the z basis, I just forget, you know,
whatever that information was, I lose that information.
I lose whether it was a plus x or a minus x
or a plus y or a minus y.
That gets thrown away and replaced
with this new stabilizer.
So I do all that to s1.
s2 through sn, it's nice.
I can just leave them alone.
They don't change.
So I just changed this one stabilizer.
So that's it.
That's the whole algorithm.
If I just do this--
and each one of these steps is simple linear algebra over f2--
I can simulate a Clifford circuit,
which is a pretty non-trivial class of quantum circuits.