Now we're going to go back to quantum error-correcting codes.
And in this lecture, we're going to do a quantum
version of the repetition code.
So 0 goes to 0 0 0.
1 goes to 1 1 1.
Well, let's try to quantumize it--
or quantize it.
0 goes to 0 0 0.
1 goes to 1 1 1, and I can write a circuit diagram for that.
So what happens?
So you already know that this is not quantum cloning
because quantum cloning is impossible.
So alpha 0 plus beta 1 goes to alpha 0 0 0 plus beta 1 1 1.
So can we correct errors?
Well, first let's try to correct the errors.
So what did this channel do?
It corrected one bit error or not channel.
What did that code do?
It corrected one bit error.
So if you flip one bit you can get it back.
So let's start out by trying sigma z errors.
Or sigma x errors.
Sigma x.
Well, we have three bits.
We can apply sigma x on it.
And so let's apply a sigma x error
to the encoded PSI on the second bit.
So PSI uncoded is equal to what?
It's equal to alpha 0 1 0 plus beta 1 0 1.
Plus beta 1 0 1.
So can we correct this?
Well, you can correct measure which bit is different?
Now you would like to measure which
bit is different without measuring all three
of these bits because if you measure all three
of these bits, you put superposition
into the code of 0 plus beta 1.
We'd like the same supervision to come out of the code
after you've decoded it.
So how do you measure which is this different?
Well, actually that's pretty easy.
So here is our encoded psi.
I encoded and we apply a control naught from the first bit
to the second but a control up from the first
to the third bit.
Back here we apply a control naught
from the first to the second and the control
naught from the first to the third.
You get 0.
You get a so 0 0-- alpha 0 0 0 plus beta 1 1 1
goes to alpha 0 0 0 plus beta 1 0 0, and you measure two zeros.
So that's good.
And you can see that this decoding circuit is really
the inverse of the encoding circuit.
So that's very good.
And now, what do we have here?
Sigma x.
Well, what happens if you made acute an error there?
Alpha so suppose you put alpha 0 1 0 plus beta 1
0 1 into that circuit.
Sign error maybe equals that.
When you put it into that circuit, you get out alpha 0 1
0 plus beta 1 1 0 because you're doing the control naught
from this guy who this guy and from the first guy
to the third guy.
And you measure 1 0 and your state is alpha 0 plus beta 1
because this is equal to alpha 0 plus beta 1 times 1 0
and you're measuring these guys.
From so what you measure tells you
that your second bit is wrong, and you've
recovered the first bit.
So suppose you put in alpha 1 0 0 plus
beta 0 1 1 so that's our error state.
So we've got this by applying sigma x to the first qubit.
After circuit, you get alpha 1 1 1 plus beta 0 1 1
is equal to alpha 1 plus beta 0 times 1 1.
And of course, you measure 1 1.
So what do you need to do to this state to fix it?
Yeah?
Apply z?
Apply?
I'm sorry.
Apply x.
So if these are both ones, these measurement results
are both ones.
You apply x here.
And maybe I should draw classical stop and green.
So that's how you decode the qubit
but of course, not everything is a sigma x error.
There's also sigma z errors.
So what happens if we apply a sigma z error to this code?
Well, there are three things you could apply the sigma z to.
The first, second, or third qubit.
What do we get?
Well, here we get alpha 0 0 0 minus beta 1 1 1.
Here we get alpha 0 0 0 minus well
it's the same thing, right?
And here we get the same thing again.
And all of these are encoded alpha 0 minus beta 1.
So what have we done?
Well, so we'll call this the bit error correcting code.
3 qubit bit error correction.
Well, if you have sigma x corrected
and if you have a sigma z, you've
applied sigma z to the encoded qubit.