So let's give some examples.
So one of them I mentioned, which is N of rho is equal to,
let's say, U rho U dagger, just unitary evolution, right?
We should always make sure that these basic ones
fit within our model.
So here there's a single Kraus operator, which is U. Right?
And then you can check U dagger U is equal to identity.
So unitary evolution fits this model.
OK, what about something a little bit more complicated?
Suppose I have random unitary evolution.
So this was the type of noise considered in 8 370.
I apply a unitary, but I draw it from some probability
distribution.
So with some probability I apply U1, with some probability
I apply U2, et cetera.
So what are the Kraus operators in this case?
Right.
So now the Kraus operators are square root of p sub e times U
sub e.
When you put it into the sum, the U e dagger U e
just becomes identity.
And the crucial thing to remember
is that we have to have square root, because it
shows up twice.
So then we get sum over e of p sub e, which just adds up to 1.
OK, so I haven't fully erased this
for a reason, which is now it's time
to talk about partial trace.
So if I trace out system b, then I've written this formula here.
And you'll notice this already has the Kraus form.
Right?
This partial trace, I've written it
as a sum over some set of a matrix on the left side
and the dagger of that matrix on the right-hand side.
OK, so already that that is in Kraus form.
The only thing to check--
let me erase this down here.
So in other words, let me call it V sub b,
is identity tensor ket b.
This is identity on Alice.
So we can just check that sum over b of V b dagger V b
is equal to sum over b of--
oh, whoa, sorry.
This is-- the V b acts on the left.
So this should be bra b.
So this sum here is sum over b of identity, tensor ket
b [AUDIO OUT] b.
The sum also gives us the identity.
So what we're left with is identity on Alice,
tensor identity on Bob.
So we can check that the conditions here are satisfied
by these Kraus operators.
So this is something that you of course cannot render
as a mixture of unitaries.
It doesn't even preserve dimension.
But there are other ones that do preserve dimension that you
still cannot write as a mixture of unitaries.
One crucial feature about unitaries
is that if you act on the maximally mixed state, the one
proportional to identity, it leaves you
with the maximally mixed state.
And so that can be thought of as infinite temperature dynamics.
Right?
If I'm in counter--
if a bath has infinite temperature,
then every state is equally likely
when I am in counter with it.
And so if I thermalize with an infinite-temperature bath,
then I will thermalize to a state
where each energy level is equally likely.
But if I thermalize with a finite-temperature bath,
then the lower energy levels will
have more population in them than the higher energy levels.
So when I cool the water in this bottle,
hopefully there's more probability
of being in the lower energy states.
And a mixture of unitaries is not going to do that.
So one thing that's sort of the ultimate refrigerator
is to map everything to a pure state.
So let's consider that example.
N of rho is just the zero state.
So this is something which is far
from the mixture of unitaries paradigm,
but is crucial if we want to, say, initialize a quantum
computer.
Right?
So you get some qubits that come in, maybe hot,
you want to cool them down, put them all in the zero state--
that is the operation that you want to do.
So what are the Kraus operators for it?
Let's say that the input is a qubit,
then there are two Kraus operators.
Let's call them--
V0 is the ket 0 bra 0.
V1 is ket 0 bra 1.
And so you can check that V0 rho V0 dagger plus V1 rho V1
dagger--
you can verify that if you put these in you
will always get output 0, regardless
of the initial state.
I won't go through that calculation,
but it's worth doing yourself if you
want to solidify this concept.
And there are others which I will put off
to the problem set.
One very important channel is called
the depolarizing channel.
And this one you can write as a mixture of unitaries,
although I won't mention how to do it.
And in this one, you've taken a state which is a qubit state.
With probability p you do nothing.
You leave it alone.
And with probability p, you throw out the state
and replace it with a maximally mixed one.
So you can think of this as the simplest
model of kind of white noise affecting your qubit.
With probability p, your qubit is completely
destroyed and replaced by a totally random one.
So when we talk about correcting quantum errors,
this is not always the most physically realistic noise
model, but it's kind of the mathematically simplest one.
If you first worry about fixing depolarizing noise,
you're on your way to thinking about noise in general.
In real life, the noise is a little bit asymmetric.
So if the qubit levels are defined by energy levels,
you are more likely to have the phase information randomized
than which energy level being randomized.
So that means that z errors, in practice,
can be much more common than x errors.
But that's sort of a second order consideration.
So first, if you can fix depolarizing noise,
then you're happy.
Then later, you make things more efficient
and you focus on the fact that some errors
are more common than others.
There's one more channel which I actually won't even
write down the definition of, I just want to mention.
And this will also be discussed on the homework-- is
the amplitude damping channel.
This one cannot be written as a mixture of unitaries.
And it corresponds-- you can think of it as corresponding
to an atom that's in a superposition of a ground
state and an excited state.
And this atom has a property that if it's in the ground
state, it just sits there.
That's what ground states do.
But if it's in the excited state,
then it will fall down to the ground state at some rate,
and in the process emit a photon.
So this is something that the environment will measure.
It will notice if a photon has been emitted.
And when that happens, you definitely
end up in the ground state.
And so this is something that, in the limit, if you apply it
for long enough, will always push you to the ground state.
But if you run it for a finite amount of time,
if you start in the excited state,
you'll still have some amplitude of remaining in the excited
state.
So it does not completely destroy the information.
And it's a physically very relevant form of noise.
And to model it, arguably Kraus operators
are one of the more natural ways of doing it.