So this is a great simplification,
because an ensemble has an infinite number
of degrees of freedom.
A density matrix has only d-- is only d square numbers.
And so if it's qubits, then that's
just a two by two matrix.
That's much simpler.
On the other hand, there's something
a little bit unsatisfactory about the definition of density
matrices that I've given.
So what we would like is we would
like a more mathematical definition of density matrices.
You could say that this definition here
is a little bit like an operational definition, right?
If I ask you what is a density matrix, you would say,
well, it's a matrix of this form,
meaning RHO is the density matrix,
if there exists an ensemble of quantum states,
with probability px and states si
x, such that if I write out this expression, I get RHO.
So that's a perfectly valid way of defining density matrices,
but it's a little bit cumbersome, right?
If I just write down a square full of numbers,
how can you tell me if that's a density matrix?
You know, how do I know if there's some ensemble that
corresponds to that?
It's not immediately obvious just
from looking at a matrix, whether it's of the right form.
Whereas, if you go back to the other entries of this table,
if I give you a vector, you can check is the norm equal to one,
or a bunch of probabilities.
Do they add up to one?
Are they nonnegative?
We would like a similarly mathematically easy to check
definition of density matrices.
And one-- the usual definition is the following.
We say that RHO is a density matrix
if trace RHO is equal to one, and RHO
is positive semidefinite.
So--
So this greater than or equal to zero
notation, or PSD, means that the matrix
is positive semidefinite.
And this is something which there--
OK.
So what does positive semidefinite mean?
There are three equivalent definitions of this.
So PSD means either that the eigenvalues--
sorry, let me--
PSD means that RHO is Hermitian.
And there are three more conditions, all of which
are equivalent.
So you can either ask that the eigenvalues are all
created equal to zero.
You can ask that if you take any expectation of RHO,
or if you think of it as a quadratic form,
you always get something which is nonnegative.
So x RHO x is greater than zero for all states x.
And there's a third more mathematical definition,
which says that RHO 10 factorize as the product of a matrix
A times it's dagger.
One way to think about these is in terms
of getting to think of why these are naturals to think
about the case when the dimension is one,
and you have a one by one matrix.
And then this is-- you just have a number, saying that Hermitian
means that it's a real number.
And then saying that it's positive
semidefinite, in each case corresponds
to the number being nonnegative, right?
If it's one by one, the matrix is--
that number is the eigenvalues.
So that should be greater than or equal to zero.
This property right here is also equivalent to that
being a nonnegative number.
And, finally, this says that the number
can be written as a complex number
times a complex conjugate which, again, is true if
and only if the number is not negative.
But, of course, PSD generalizes this to matrices.
So this is a mathematical characterization
of density matrices.
Above, I gave an operational one,
and I claim that those are equivalent.
In other words, if you have a density matrix,
it can be written in this way.
It satisfies these properties.
Treyf RHO is one.
RHO is positive semidefinite.
And vice-versa.
If I have a matrix RHO that satisfies these properties,
there exists a corresponding ensemble.
That's a nontrivial statement, so
to prove that takes a little bit of work.
And that's something I'm going to skip right here, because I
assume either you've seen it or, if not, that you'll review it.
So if you haven't seen it before,
I just wanted to highlight that it's not obvious
that that's true.
However, it is true.
So these are two ways of thinking about this lower right
box can be either an ensemble, which has a density matrix,
or you can just define density matrices directly
without the need for ensemble.