There's one more application I want
to describe of the symplectic picture, which
is a way of simulating a quantum circuit
on a classical computer.
Normally, you would think that if I have a quantum
circuit on n qubits, I just have to write down
a state of dimension 2 to the n, and that's
going to take me time 2 to the n,
and every step is going to take time 2 to the n.
And my memory requirements are also large.
It's just really hard, and this is, of course,
the early motivation for building quantum computers.
And then you might say, well, there
are special classes of computation
where this is not true.
For example, if I only have single cubic gates,
I just need to write down the state of each qubit.
I don't have to worry about entanglement,
and that's going to be a much smaller amount of memory
and time.
But then you might say, well, looks
like entanglement is responsible for the power of quantum
computing.
Entanglement is what gives us these 2
to the n dimensional vectors, and that
is where the hardness of stimulation comes from.
And that intuition, I think, has a large inner product
with the truth, but it's not quite true.
Because the Gottesman-Knill theorem describes a large class
of non-trivial computations that you can do,
which can, nevertheless, be totally simulated classically,
and these are the Clifford's circuits.
And technically, to talk about a simulation,
I have to also talk about how you initialize it and measure.
So Gottesman-Knill says, let's say
I start with the all zero string.
I apply some Clifford unitary.
I measure, let's say, the first qubit in the v basis.
And then I repeat.
So I go back to this step, and now under my remaining qubits,
I do some other unitary, and then I do another measurement,
and I do what are called even an adaptive computation.
So I measure one qubit, but I still have many qubits left
that are uncollapsed.
I can do further Cliffords on those,
and all this I claim can be simulated.
So all this there exists an efficient classical simulation.
By efficient I mean time that's less than n,
that's less than some polynomial of n.
So this is interesting for a few reasons.
First, just conceptually, the Clifford group
can make a lot of entanglement.
You can do a zero then Hadamard and then control not,
then you have a bell pair.
And you can get GHC states and many body entangled states.
Pretty complicated states that are definitely very entangled
can come out of Clifford circuits.
And so this argues, it's not just the entanglement.
What is exactly the secret ingredient
behind quantum speed up?
It's something which I don't think
we have a short answer to, and definitely Gottesman-Knill
is part of what makes the question complicated.
So on a conceptual level about the power of quantum
computing is interesting.
It's also always nice of efficient algorithms.
Now, the Clifford circuits are not
universal for quantum computing, so we can't use this
to simulate Shor's algorithm.
We probably would have heard about it by now.
But you can use it to simulate Clifford's circuits
and those are useful, as we'll see in the next section,
for fault tolerant quantum computing.
And so if you want to know how does your error correction
scheme work in the presence of poly errors,
and your error correction is based on Clifford gates,
can simulate that on hundreds of qubits
using a classical computer.
And so that's pretty useful to be
able to go beyond to have something that's
more efficient than just full simulation of the wave vector.