So next, I want to tell you about what
happens to the dephasing channel when you
look at it in the Bloch sphere.
So let's go back and draw the Bloch sphere.
So the Bloch sphere looked like 0, 1, plus minus--
well, when you multiply the off-diagonal elements by q,
you get 1, 1, 1, 1, that's 1/2, goes to 1/2 1, 1 minus q,
1 minus q, 1.
And with that, you're just moving the Bloch sphere
into the middle, because you're taking this,
you're multiplying it by 1 minus q,
and you're adding q amount of diagonal.
Or q amount of the identity.
So that goes here.
And in general, this is going to go to an ellipsoid.
This is still zero.
This is still 1.
And this is 1, 1 minus q, 1 minus q, 1, et cetera.
So you shrink the Bloch sphere into an ellipsoid
with the vertical axis stays the same and everything else
shrinks by the same factor.
So this is the phasing in Bloch picture.