On the other hand, we can talk about measurements,
and to keep things simple, let me just
talk about a two outcome measurement.
So there are two outcomes, m and i minus m.
Remember that measurement of a set of matrices
have to add up to the identity.
Also, each of these matrices has to be positive semidefinite
so we need to have m greater than or equal to zero,
and i minus m greater than or equal to zero.
This second condition, of course,
is the same as saying that m is less than
or equal to the identity matrix.
So we can put these together as saying
that m is in between zero and the identity
in the positive semidefinite ordering.
And if m is a positive semidefinite matrix,
again, the singular values are the eigenvalues.
So the biggest singular value is just the biggest eigenvalue.
And so saying that m is less or equal to identity,
that says all the eigenvalues are at most one.
That's the same in this setting as saying that the Schatten
infinity norm is at most one.
So now the set of allowable measurement operators
has a description that looks kind of like the density
matrices, except here we use s infinity instead of s one.
Also this is less than or equal to one instead of equal to one.
So instead of the unit sphere, we
call this the unit ball of s infinity.
You know, it's like the filled in sphere.
And, so there is a probabilistic analog as well,
which is that for every event you
could assign it a value anywhere between minus one and one.
And this corresponds to sort of a decision rule.
If you're given a sample from something,
if you want to decide yes or no about some consequence of it.
So OK, so why is it that measurements
are described by this one norm and states
are described by another one?
This fact that you have one norm for one type of object
or another norm for another type of object,
and furthermore that these objects naturally will
combine with each other, right?
So we often will write trace of m times row.
Right, this is the probability of observing outcome m given
density matrix row.
So these things are often essentially innerproducted
with each other.
In fact, we can even write this as a sort of inner product
on matrices.
So we have these two things that are naturally
innerproducted with each other.
But one of them gets measured with one norm,
another with another norm.
And this phenomenon occurs in a much more general sense
under the name of duality.
let me define very generally what it means to have,
given a norm, to have a dual norm.
So given some norm, I'll just write
by these double absolute value signs,
we can define what's called a dual norm.
In the following sense, the dual norm
will be denoted by norms of star.
And what the dual norm is, for that vector x,
it's the largest inner product you can have with something
in the unit ball of this norm.
This is the maximum over y less than
or equal to one of the inner product of x with y.
Absolute value.
OK?
So here's how to think about it.
This norm is a way of measuring the length of a vector.
It gives me a way of measuring the length of another vector
to say what is the largest inner product I can
have with something that has length one with respect
to this norm?
So you've seen this before from the L2 norm.
So you know if I have a vector, one of the biggest
inner products it can have within any unit
vector in the usual Euclidean sense, and that inner product,
that number is just the length of the vector in the Euclidean
sense.
So in other words, the L2 norm is dual to the L2 norm.
So L2 is self-dual.
Its dual is itself.
On the other hand.
L1 and L infinity are dual.
So if I, let's say this original norm is L infinity.
And I say, so the unit ball of l infinity
are things where every entry is between minus one and one.
And I say, given a vector x, if I want an inner product it
with something where every entry is between minus one and one,
how big can I make that inner product?
What I can do is I can just set y
to be the sign, each entry of y to be
the sign of the corresponding entry of x.
So this inner product becomes the sum of the entries of x.
In other words, it becomes the one norm of x.
So I started with the infinity norm, I took the dual,
and I got the one norm.
If you go in the other direction,
take the one norm, the dual of that
will be the L infinity norm.
And there is a formula in general,
every LP norm is dual to some LQ norm.
There's a formula for it which I won't get into,
but this is more generally LP norms are dual to LQ norms
for some other Q. Two is special, that's
the only one that is self-dual.
So the reason I mention this, is the same
is true for the Schatten norms.
So S1 and S infinity are also dual.
In general if LP and LQ are dual,
then SP and SQ are also dual.
And this is something that is actually
an optional problem on your problem set,
to help you understand a little more the geometry of a set
of states and density matrices.
It's a little bit harder to visualize,
but I often go back to this picture of L1 and L
infinity when I think about what these things look like.
S1 and S infinity, the geometry is like the matrix version