The term stabilizer is used in quantum information
in sometimes a slightly misleading way.
And let me-- I'll show you how that is in a minute.
It's often used to mean two things,
but the first is, it's often used to mean
a subgroup of the poly group.
So let me begin by defining.
P sub n will be the real-valued Paulis on n qubits.
So what do I mean by that?
What I mean is, plus or minus identity, X, iY, and Z,
then the n-fold tensor power of this.
So I have n qubits.
I can have, on each qubit, either identity, X, iY, or Z.
And I can also have an overall phase of plus or minus.
I'm putting the iY here because I want to deal only
with real-valued matrices.
And you can check that this is a closed group, right?
If I multiply X times Z, I get iY.
If I multiply x times iY, I get minus
Z. So I never-- if I multiply two real-valued Pauli matrices,
I get something else which is real.
And this avoids me having to deal with imaginary numbers.
Which is not really a big deal-- all of this stuff could go
through with imaginaries--
it's just slightly simpler to not use them.
So this is a group, meaning it's closed under multiplication
and contains inverses.
In fact, every element of this group is its own inverse.
And it's, of course, not a commuting group-- you know,
the Paulis do not commute with each other.
And what a stabilizer--
so we'll talk about many stabilizer-related things.
A stabilizer subgroup is a subgroup of the Pauli matrices
with various properties.