Before I give examples, I want to prove one more thing
about them.
So what I've derived is that if you have an isometry--
sorry.
If you have a quantum channel defined
by an isometry, and then a partial trace,
then there exists also a Kraus operator description of it.
To be complete, we should go in the other direction as well.
We should say if I have a quantum channel described
by Kraus operators, satisfying the Kraus operator condition,
then that's equivalent to one of that form,
that there exists an isometry.
So conversely, given a set of Kraus operators, and of rho,
this map should be a valid quantum operation.
Does anyone see why that should be true?
If I satisfy these conditions, why
should that imply that I can also write it in this form?
So, right.
The comment was, I can construct V as follows,
I'm given these Ve.
I could just write down the corresponding V.
And then I claim this is an isometry.
Why is that?
Well, I'm just running the same argument backwards
that I had over here.
So I start with this condition, and then this
is the Kraus operator condition.
This is also equal to what I get from V dagger V.
So if I satisfy the Kraus operator conditions,
then the V I've written down over there must be an isometry,
and it also corresponds to this quantum channel.
So everything I did, basically, you could run either forward
or backwards to map between these two different pictures.