Peter Shor came out with his algorithm for factoring numbers
and the whole community was really floored and surprised
by this discovery, but immediately reacted
by saying it's a beautiful theoretical discovery that
will never be practical and never
be implemented because quantum systems are
so susceptible to noise.
There are three things that were pointed out about this.
So if I start summarizing quantum coding, as of 1995,
quantum coding-- the analog of quantum to classical codes--
were considered impossible because of three major reasons.
First, states collapse when measured.
Remember a0 plus b1, when measured,
just give you 0 and 1 with some probabilities.
So you lose that information about a
and b for a single instance of it.
And you only have a and b when you have an ensemble.
You don't actually get a and b from a single instance
of a message, in contrast to what you might
get from a classical system.
So this also means that you can't just
measure by seeing what message you got
and then doing a majority vote on it.
So if I'm doing a classical code, I might say,
if I'm doing a classicals code, I might say,
if I'm doing a classical code, I might say something three times
to make sure that you understand it.
I'll say it three times so that you
make sure you understand it.
I'll say it two times to make sure that you understand it.
Of course, you can do a majority vote
and figure out what I actually meant,
even though I screw up once.
But that's because you listened to and deciphered the message.
If I'm doing it quantum mechanically, I cannot do that.
So people said that's one reason why
there's going to be no such thing as quantum error
correction codes.
You can't build a quantum repetition code.
The second thing is that we have this model
for errors over here, the binary symmetric channel.
So you either have an error or you did not have an error.
But in the quantum realm, errors aren't so nice to you.
Errors are continuous.
For example, rotations-- a qubit could
move just an infinitesimal amount on the block sphere.
Is that an error or not an error,
if you just rotated by an epsilon amount?
It's very different from this binary symmetric channel.
So it is also well known that analog signals don't really
have error correction.
You have to move into the world of digital signal
processing and digital signals to get
this kind of correction code.
So a great analogy was made between analog computation
and quantum computation saying that, just
as analog computation is unstable,
quantum computers will also be unstable,
and therefore, quantum algorithms like Shor's
algorithm will be impractical.
The third objection was the fact that, even
if you did want to build a quantum repetition code,
there's something that prohibits this.
Remember we went into this very early on in the class
right away, and that is the no cloning theorem.
Quantum states, if they are unknown, cannot be copied.
So three major constraints, three major objections
to the existence of quantum error correction,
even in principle--
and one of the neat things is that Peter Shor did not
mention these three objections because it
was so obvious to him, perhaps, how to overcome them.
But for the rest of us in the community
for whom it wasn't so obvious, it
was remarkable to see how they were overcome.
And in fact, a little bit of history
is that they were overcome by Peter Shor.
So Peter Shor wrote a second paper after his factoring paper
showing how quantum error correction could be done.
By the way, just in terms of the history,
after error correction, the next objection
that people came up with was that there's
no way to make it resilient against failures in gates.
So this is resiliency against errors
in states and in communication, but not about resiliency
in, like, if the unitary operator is slightly wrong
and rotates slightly more or slightly less
or around the wrong axis.
That is a concept known as fault tolerance.
So even though error correction was
shown to be possible by Peter Shor in a manner
that I'll review more about in just a moment,
the next piece of the story, the next missing piece of this,
was fault tolerance.
So Peter Shor went and wrote a third paper
showing how one could present and construct
fault-tolerant quantum computation.
And it took the rest of the better
of part of maybe a decade to unravel all of those results
and understand them.
And so it is because of those three incredible pieces of work
that Peter Shor is known as such a master of the field today.
And I'm only going to show you part of it.
And the thing I want to show you now
is how these three objections are overcome.
The first of these objections is overcome
by realizing that you don't need to measure the state.
So instead of measuring the state, what we will do
is to employ two strategies.
The first is never to measure the state,
and only measure the environment and its effect--
that is, the error.
All you want to do is find out what the error was.
You don't necessarily care what state was encoded,
and in fact you don't want to figure that out.
Because then you would lose the quantum information
that you're trying to protect.
But the whole concept of measuring
the effect of the environment separate
from measuring the state that's encoded was a novel one.
So this fixes objection number one.
The second idea, which now we use routinely in quantum error
correction but was not conceptualized yet
at the time of Peter Shor's first article
about error correction, is two orthogonalize errors.
Such that if you have a small rotation, you can either think
of it as being a complete flip or no flip at all.
And you're able to do this if you employ entanglement.
And I'm not going to describe the formalism behind this
to you, but I will try to post on the class site
a beautiful paper by John Preskill titled
"How to Fight Entanglement with Entanglement."
You fight the entanglement caused
by the environment that's making errors on the quantum state
with a different kind of entanglement, which
is the entanglement that exists within the codewords
and inside the code space.
So it's a beautiful concept, and I
hope you'll be able to see where it arises as I go forward.