There's something that we did here where we kind of-- it
looked more beautiful than we needed, in a sense.
So what we needed is, when there's an error,
you can figure it out and correct the error.
But what we got is every error you can figure out
exactly which one it is, and each one
leads to a distinct syndrome.
And this property is called being non-degenerate.
So a non-degenerate code means that any correctable error
leads to a distinct syndrome.
And from what I've argued, that seems pretty necessary, right?
Because if there are two errors that lead to the same syndrome,
I cannot distinguish them.
So my recovery cannot do anything different.
And yet-- so let me just define a degenerate code--
sometimes different errors have the same syndrome.
So at its face, that does not sound good,
because I cannot distinguish these errors.
And that is true, right?
If I have two errors, E1 and E2, they
give rise to the same syndrome.
When I correct it, maybe I'm undoing E1,
or maybe I'm undoing E2.
So let's suppose this happens.
So suppose E1 and E2 are different,
and they have the same syndrome.
Then when I correct--
and suppose E1 happens, and I apply E2.
Let's say E2 done.
So what happens is psi gets mapped to E1 psi, and in turn
to E2 dagger, e1 psi.
So it sounds like I'm laying out the problem
with degenerate codes.
Can anyone see in a reason why this might still be OK?
[INAUDIBLE]
He said use the error correcting criteria,
which is on the right track.
But can you say more about that, or what you get from that?
[INAUDIBLE]
Well, yes.
But in that case, you would want to get to zero.
But why you get zero is not totally obvious in this case.
So let's just see what happens when a Pauli acts on your code.
That Pauli it could cause a logical error, right?
And then this would be a catastrophe.
Then this little noise happened, I
would have corrected it with what I thought
was doing the right thing.
But the noise plus my correction has actually
changed the encoded data.
That would be a failure of the code.
It could in principle lead to a detectable error.
But it won't, because I've fixed the syndrome.
At the end of this process, I've restored the syndrome
to being all plus one.
So this thing right here is not going
to lead to some detectable error that's going
to violate some syndrome bits.
But there's another possibility which would not
be a failure, which is we could have E2 dagger
E1 in the stabilizer group.
So it could be that yes, I made the wrong correction.
But it was wrong only up to multiplying by a stabilizer.
And we know that these are nontrivial operators that
still act trivially on the code space.
So if I make a mistake that's off by a stabilizer generator,
it doesn't matter.
I still am essentially applying the right correction
for my database.
So the five-qubit code does not have that property.
In fact, there's something kind of perfect
about the dimensions.
The code set space is two-dimensional.
The number of single-qubit errors,
there's three Pauli's times five qubits is 15, plus one
for the possibility of no error.
So there are 16 possible errors.
And so that two-dimensional space
just gets mapped to 16 different copies
for the 16 different possible errors or no error.
Two times 16 is 32.
We have five qubits.
So that's like a perfect non-degenerate code.
But degenerate codes can also be valuable,
because you're kind of taking advantage of the fact
that your stabilizer generators are sort of corrected for free.
If your error happens to be a stabilizer generator,
then just nothing happens, and you don't have to worry.
So let me just mention, this is five-qubit code.
An example of degenerate code is the nine-qubit Shor code,
as well as something that we'll see soon called the Toric code.
And in fact, it's almost necessary in a certain sense
for a class of code called LDPC codes.
OK, so LDPC is an acronym that comes from the classical coding
literature.
It means low-density parity check.
And what it means in the quantum case
is that your stabilizer generators each involve
a small number of qubits.
So imagine that your code corrects tons of errors,
but your stabilizers just look at--
I don't know, two or three or four qubits.
The idea is this is something which
is physically a lot easier to measure than something that
involves many of the qubits.
So it's physically a very desirable property of codes.
But if you have low weight stabilizer generators--
let's say weight four--
then it's very easy to have products of errors
in the stabilizer group.
Like if I have weight four things here,
E1 and E2 are weight two, already
I've got stuff that's in the stabilizer group.
And for a big enough code, I really
hope I can correct two errors.
So I can very quickly get into a situation
where products of errors and relatively few qubits
are in the stabilizer group.
And this is basically inevitable when
I have quantum LDPC codes, of which we'll see
an example is the Toric code.
So this degenerate property at first does not sound so good.
But later, we see it's almost inevitable if we want codes