Last time, we talked about the states of quantum information.
And we can view density matrices as
a simultaneous generalization of both pure-state quantum
mechanics and classical probability theory.
Today, I want to talk about dynamics.
We saw that there were these, in the different models,
there's various versions of dynamics.
In probability theory, you have stochastic maps.
In pure-state quantum mechanics, you
have unitary transformations.
And today, we'll talk about quantum operations, which
are the ones that apply to density matrices, this most
general of the possible states, once you take both quantum
mechanics and probability into account.
So at the end of last lecture, I gave you a few examples.
Today, I want to give a complete characterization.
Actually, I want to have three complete characterizations.
So I'll begin with the first one that's known as the Stinespring
representation of a channel.
That's just a name.
What's significant about this one is that it's operational.
So this first one corresponds to the way
you may think of a quantum operation actually happening
in the world.
Especially if you're used to the Schrodinger equation,
this will be the one that is the most natural.
It's the most natural physically in some ways,
but it's not always the most natural to calculate with.
So the second definition I'll mention,
which follows naturally from the first one,
is called the Kraus operator representation.
And this one has the advantage of being the simplest
to write down.
And in calculations, it's often the first one
that you want to use.
Once we're armed with this, I'll be able to give some examples
of quantum channels, both some that you've seen before in this
formalism, as well as some that you haven't.
Finally, I'll give a third definition,
which is a more axiomatic one.
So we're used to--
for stochastic matrices, you can think of them
as these are the linear maps that keep things
non-negative and summing to 1.
For unitary matrices, these are the linear maps
that preserve the Euclidean length of a vector.
So we can similarly taken axiomatic approach
to quantum channels, and this describes quantum operations
as TCPC maps, trace-preserving completely positive maps.
I'll say more about what that means later.
Finally, I'll talk about one very important special case
of quantum operations, which are ones
have a quantum input and a classical output,
otherwise known as measurements.
And I'll use this way of describing
them to explain a little bit more
about the geometry of quantum states and measurements
in terms of various matrix norms.
Any questions before I begin?