Now, I want to move on to talk about quantum operations.
In other words, what dynamics are possible in quantum theory?
So this is the state space.
And these are states where we haven't said how they change,
right?
We got them somehow, maybe we'll measure them.
But we've made no statement about how
either our conscious actions are going to change them,
or they will inevitably change in their own internal
evolution, or some unwanted noise will affect them.
All of these are things we have to study beyond just
the basic state spaces.
And the set of available operations
will depend on what type of theory.
And so I want to build up to the operations
we do on density matrices by reviewing
the possible operations on these other theories
in the other three cells of the box.
So again, we can make this grid.
Classical, quantum, deterministic, random.
So, what can we say about the operations
in these other cells?
So if I have a deterministic theory, has d possible states,
what are the possible transitions?
So I haven't told you much, right?
I haven't said anything about physically what they are
or how we're doing these transitions.
All I'm saying is that you should
start with a deterministic state,
and end with a deterministic state.
I'm going to stay within the theory
of deterministic classical states.
So what can you say about the available transitions?
How would you describe them mathematically?
What's that?
A matrix, right.
With, what about the matrix?
You could say it has a matrix of zeros and ones, maybe.
Right, because each state should be mapped to one other state.
Another, maybe even simpler way of doing it,
is you could say you have functions.
From the set 1 through d, mapping to the set 1 through d.
And you could represent these functions as a matrix,
like you said, or you could just say those are my operations.
They are functions that map the set 1 through d
to the set 1 through d.
Tells you almost nothing.
One important feature of this is that this
could destroy information.
So if I have a bit of valid operation,
I can do to it is ignore the input and output zero.
Right, so the erase operation Is a valid operation
I can do to bits.
What about deterministic quantum states?
So if I have a state, psi, what are
the physically possible ways that this can evolve in time?
From the Schrodinger equation, what kinds of time evolution
are possible?
Unitary matrices, right.
So the operations here, we can write is as U of d.
Meaning d by d, unitary matrices.
Mathematically, these are the operations
that are linear on psi, and preserve the length.
So psi is a unit vector.
After some time evolution, it had better
remain a unit vector.
And so, the linear operations, If you're a linear operation,
then you can be described as a matrix.
And if you preserve the length, then that
means you should be a unitary matrix.
And so, the linearity here, by the way,
is we've already used it a few times.
So we're using it to get unitarity.
It was also implicit in our description
of density matrices.
So I said for density matrices that observables only
depend linearly on this combination of ket-psi bra-psi.
And if you want to do something crazy,
like go to a nonlinear quantum mechanics,
you would have to abandon that.
And so this is kind of deeply embedded
into all of our assumptions that quantum mechanics is linear.
Yeah?
Your [INAUDIBLE].
By nature.
But, the classical bits, we don't have the evolution
equation for that, right?
[INAUDIBLE]
Well, right.
So the question is, the Schrodinger equation comes
from nature, where does this function f come from?
The way I would say is the Schrodinger equation comes
from nature, and then when we integrate it,
we obtain some unitary.
In classical mechanics, I'm skipping over
the microscopic derivation of how things evolve.
You can imagine some Newtonian mechanics, or whatever
your favorite classical theory is, and then you integrate that
and you'll get some kind of effective dynamics.
And then you could abstract that in this way.
So, you could think of this is an abstraction
of Newtonian dynamics that says the particles have
some initial position of momenta.
There is some deterministic way that they
evolve to some later position and momenta.
And you could imagine, maybe Newtonian mechanics
doesn't destroy information, you could
imagine modifications of it that destroy information as well.
Like sometimes particles get lost.
the
Other way to think about this is emerging from a computer.
So if I wanted to describe what a classical computer does,
it looks like this type of operation.
And that's maybe a more realistic way
of thinking about it.
And then you can ask about what are Maxwell's laws
that underlie the function of a classical computer.
But if you just want to abstract away from those
and talk about the information carrying properties,