Once you've defined the stabilizer group,
s, to understand which errors are detected by it,
you should do that in terms of the normalizer group.
So, N of s, recall is the set of polys such that--
well, one way of writing it is that p s p dagger
is equal to s, as a sort of set-wise operation.
So this means that if I take this set, s,
and I multiply every element in it
by p on the left and p dagger on the right,
I get back the original set, s.
Now-- and so I'm looking at all polys, p,
that have this property.
Now, polys, remember-- they either commute or anti-commute.
So, if I have anything in s that anti-commutes with p,
I'm going to get back negative of that element.
And, you remember, the stabilizer groups
do not contain negative identity.
So that means, if they contain some element,
they do not contain the negation of that element.
So, if I contain, you know, g, I do not also contain minus g.
So this is equivalent--
so this statement right here is the equivalent
of saying that p g equals g p, for all g in the stabilizer
group.
OK?
It's just another way of saying that I
want the set of polys that commutes with everything
in the stabilizer group.
And because a stabilizer group is Abelian,
the normalizer always contains a stabilizer group.
But there can be more things in it as well.
So, for this group, there are two more elements
that we can add.
And one way to see them is, if you
remember this linear algebra point of view--
so let me write l of s to be a subspace of f2 to 5--
I mean, the-- this means the linear subspace corresponding
to s.
And in that case, l of n of s is just the orthogonal complement
of l of s.
Remember, last time we defined the symplectic inner product.
And we said that the polys commute
if their corresponding vectors are orthogonal--
have inner product zero.
So the set of all polys that commute with everything in s--
when you translate into vector language,
you're saying, take all the vectors corresponding to s
and ask for the set of things which is perpendicular to that.
And so that's, basically, what this perp symbol means.
It means take a subspace.
Take everything perpendicular to that.
This is probably a good time to mention
that, when I said that F2 was a field,
and you can do linear algebra over it,
most of what you learned about linear algebra
for the reals and complex numbers will carry over.
But there's a few little oddities.
One of them is that you can have a non-zero vector which
is orthogonal to itself.
In fact, s is an entire subspace full of vectors that are all
orthogonal to themselves--
well, in fact, to each other.
Everything in the subspace is orthogonal to everything else
in the subspace, because this is an Abelian group.
So that's just a little oddity to keep
in mind about F2 linear algebra, which is not present,
of course, in the reals and complex numbers.
OK, so how can we find this subspace?
The hint is that it's orthogonal to these vectors.
So, basically, you want something which,
if you look at the inner product of--
wherever there are x's, compare wherever the new vector is,
where there are x's.
Look at the corresponding z's, here, and they should--
that number of overlaps, plus the number
of overlaps of the z's in the new word with x's here--
that should be even.
And so you could do this just by doing F2 linear algebra.
Or you could just--
I could just tell you a vector.
And you can verify that it works.
And so, to do it the quick way, I'll
tell you that one vector that's in it is the 5x operator.
So if I take a string of all x's, you
can see, for every one of these cyclically shifted codewords,
it's going to commute with the x's in it.
And there are two z's.
So, two z's means inner product of zero.
1 plus 1 here is 0.
And the same logic would apply to the 5z operator.
So, for the same reason, the 5z operator is in n of s.
And these are not members of s, because, however I multiply
these together, I'm going to have an even number
of x's and z's.
And these have an odd number.
So I can write n of s as being generated
by the stabilizers, plus these two additional operators.
And these operators-- so what do they do?
They commute with everything in the stabilizer set,
which means that they map this subspace to itself.
So, if I take one of these operators,
and I act on this subspace, I'm going
to map it back to the subspace.
But that doesn't mean that I fix every single vector in it,
right.
So the stabilizers fix every single vector in this subspace.
Any vector you have here, the stabilizers will act trivially.
But these things-- all we know about those is, they leave you
within the subspace.
In general, they will change the vectors within the subspace.
And so we can define--
so, I haven't told you what zero bar and one bar are.
We can just define them to be eigenstates of these operators.
So let me call this--
sorry, let me do it like this.
Let me define these operators to be z bar and x bar.
These will be the operators that act on the logical qubit,
so x bar and z bar act on logical qubit.
Before we go on, we should note that they anti-commute, right,
because they overlap in an odd number of places.
So they, really, in that sense, are
polys that look like x and z.
And, with these in hand, after having to find these,
we can just choose zero bar and one bar to be the eigenstates--
the plus or minus one eigenstates of z bar.
So we'll choose it so that zero bar zero is equal to zero--
sorry, z bar zero bar is equal to zero bar.
Z bar one bar is minus one bar.
And once we've defined them in this way,
it follows that x bar has the action that we want.
So, just knowing that x bar and z bar anti-commute,
and knowing that zero bar and one bar
are the plus and minus eigenstates of z bar,
it follows that we have this x action.
Does anyone-- can anyone see why that's true?
[INAUDIBLE]
Right.
I mean, you, basically, just write out
the anti-commutation relations, and you'll see this happens.
And, I guess, we saw that last time, right.
We saw that, when you have something that's
a plus one eigenstate of a poly, and then
you hit this with another poly, then
this first state will remain an eigenstate of the first poly.
But whether it's a plus one or minus eigenstate
may flip, depending on whether the second poly commutes
or anti-commutes.
So, if I were to hit this with something that
commuted with z bar, I would not change whether it's
a plus or minus one eigenstate.
If I hit it with something that anti-commutes,
I will flip it from a plus one to a minus one
eigenstate, and vice versa.
And the way we label these plus and minus eigenstates
are zero bar and one bar.
I mean, technically, actually, I have a little bit of--
I have a phased degree of freedom.
So that leaves open the possibility
that I put some phase in front of these.
But I can just use that phased degree of freedom
to make sure that, here, there's no phase--
you know, that I get these m instead of having any phases,
right.
Because just these equations up here
didn't fix the phase of these eigenstates.
But I can use that so that this equation becomes true.