Technically, all I've shown you is
that if you're in the Clifford group then
you can be described by a symplectic transformation,
up to this issue of phase.
We have not seen the reverse.
I claim that if you have any symplectic transformation
on F2, then there exists a Clifford
unitary that will realize it.
In other words, it will map polys
according to the desired matrix M.
And that is something I am not going to prove in class.
You will sort of prove most of the parts of this on the p-set.
So this is a claim, evidence to be supplied by you later
on the p-set.
But right now, I just want to claim
that those are equivalent.
So I claim for any symplectic M, there exists some U such
that U sigma v u dagger is plus or minus sigma
Mv for all v in F2 to the 2n.
So my claim is that if and only if,