So let me now switch to a much simpler code
that we can still learn some things from.
So the next code I want to talk about is the trivial code,
where our stabilizer space--
so the code space just looks like n minus k0's tensored
with a totally arbitrary state on k qubits.
So we get a few things out of this.
We get a reminder that a quantum code is just a subspace.
It doesn't have to have any useful properties.
This is mathematically as much a code as anything else.
Of course, its distance is not very good.
But it's no less a code than the Shor nine-qubit code.
So we can see some of this claim here illustrated
for the trivial code.
So first, let's write down the stabilizer group.
So what is the group of Paulis that
stabilize these states for which these states are plus one item
states.
Or maybe I should-- yeah, can someone
named a Pauli that stabilizes this state?
z1, right.
So if I act on this with z1, there's
a zero in the first qubit, so it's going to be a plus one.
And of course, once you've got z1,
you can imagine you get all of the z's up through n minus k.
Because you have zeros in all those positions.
And these are clearly independent also.
There's no way to make a non-trivial product
of these equal to the identity.
Are there any more stabilizers?
I mean, x1 through xn minus k doesn't
seem like that's going to work.
Anything else?
So Vs, the set of these states for all possible psi.
So it might be that for some psi,
there's something that stabilizes it.
But you would need something that works for all states spi.
Yeah?
Identity?
The identity, yes.
I usually do not list the identity
in a list of generators, because we always have it for free.
So when I say--
not so obvious I think from the terminology.
But when I say I've got a bunch of generators,
and I do this sort of bracket notation,
I mean all products of these generators.
But that includes the empty product,
which I just by definition take to be the identity.
But yes, identity definitely stabilizes everything.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]?
Yes, but that would be contained in this.
So, yeah.
People having trouble coming up with more.
I didn't want to argue that there are no more.
OK, so let's try and think about that.
Remember, so I have n minus k independent generators.
What dimension do I have for a stabilizer space?
You know, if I have a subspace stabilized
by n minus k independent polys.
Do you remember how to calculate the dimension of it?
So I start with two to the n dimensions.
Every time I add a stabilizer, what happens?
Cut it down by half.
Good so I do that n minus k times.
What am I left with?
Two to the k, right.
And what dimension is this?
Two to the k, right?
Because I'm starting with psi as a two to the k
dimensional state, and I'm applying isometry
into this larger space.
Or if you like, I can just run over a basis of this,
and each one of these are going to be orthogonal states
in the subspace.
So I don't have any room for more generators.
If I had another inventor generator,
I would cut down the dimension too low.
So that's a good way of knowing when it's time to stop.
I've figured out a bunch of generators.
And then I know by dimension counting
if I had any more, that would be too much.
So I stop here.
So these are the stabilizers.
Let's compute the normalizer group now.
So normalizer group is going to include all of S. What
are some operators that commute with everything in S
that I haven't already listed?
Pair of x's?
A pair of x's would commute with the product of all these Z's,
but would not commute with them individually.
That's a good point.
If I take x1, x2, it will not commute with Z1, for example.
But it will commute with Z1 times Z2.
Any operator in the [? q ?] to k subspace.
Any operator in what?
In the [? q to ?] k?
Right.
So any operator on these qubits.
So these are the last k qubits.
So I can put xn minus k plus 1 through xn z n minus k plus 1
through zn.
And that covers all of those qubits.
And in fact, that's everything that we have here.
Those are all of the remaining vectors.
One way we can see this, by the way-- you know, why do we
know that we can stop here?
One reason that we can see this is in terms
of linear algebra over f2.
So if you look at l of S, the dimension of l of S
is equal to n minus k.
You have a minus k dimensional stabilizer space.
And so if you look at the dimension of l of N of S,
it's going to be--
this is the space perpendicular to this one.
So what you do--
this is true in any field--
say I have a space of dimension d, the space
that's perpendicular to it is the dimension
of the ambient space minus d.
So this is going to be dimension of f2 to the 2n minus
dimension of l of S. Because it's
all the vectors in f2 to the 2n and that
are orthogonal to these.
And basically, every independent vector
here gives you a new constraint, which cuts down
the dimensionality by one.
So we're left with n plus k.
Right?
2n minus parenthesis n minus k.
So we can think of that as we have
the original n minus k from the stabilizers,
plus 2k from the logical operators.
So this is kind of another justification
of why the logical operators look
like this, why we have k logical x's and k logical Z's
corresponding to our k logical qubits.
This is sort of an example.
This trivial code is kind of an example of what
happens for a general code.
But what's nice about it, the reason
why I bother to mention it, is that it's
kind of a without loss of generality example.
So this is kind of a--
when I first saw this, I was very surprised by this fact.
But later I think it helps shed light
on the structure of these codes.
So I claim that if c is equal to VS for some stabilizer group S,
then there exists a unitary U such that U times the code
space is equivalent to the trivial code.
I don't know why I wrote equivalence.
Is equal to the trivial code space.
And when you act on a subspace, the stabilizer group
also transforms.
So the UC is stabilized by USU dagger.
And so I claim that this of course
would be equal to the group generated by Z1 through Z n
minus k for some k.
Well actually, for k equal log the dimension of c.