Let me get some examples.
So I argued last time that if you have a classical code,
it's always stabilized by some product of these.
So one easy example of this, suppose our subspace is just
the span of the 00 vector.
Then this is stabilized by--
basically, it's not stabilized by any x or y terms.
If I multiply by x, it's going to change one of the zeros
to a 1.
Same if I multiply by y, up to a phase.
But it is stabilized by the z's.
And in fact, any product of these.
So the stabilizer group I can write like this.
It's these four operators are the things that
stabilize this subspace, this one-dimensional subspace.
And you'll notice that there's a little bit of redundancy here.
Because this is a subgroup, if I just list a few of these,
then I get for free all of their products.
And so I could write this also using this notation.
The brackets here mean the group generated.
So this means group generated by IZ and ZI.
So whatever is inside the bracket,
just take all ways of multiplying them together--
including taking none of them and getting the identity--
and that means it's the group generated by these elements.
So if I just take these two elements, which stabilize this,
they generate these four things in S.
And here it says small savings, but it for a larger stabilizer
group, it can be a big savings.
And this is, of course, essentially a special case
of what we saw last time with classical codes.
But you can also get some non-classical states
stabilized in this way.
So another example is the [INAUDIBLE] tangled state.
And what is it stabilized by?
We know it's stabilized by ZZ because it applies at no phase
here, and it applies minus 1 twice to this state.
So it acts trivially here.
And it's also stabilized by XX.
Because XX will switch 00 and 11.
And so it will leave this state unchanged.
And of course, we should make sure that these commute.
X and Z anti-commute.
But XX and ZZ commute because their commutator picks up
two copies of minus 1, which gives you 1.
And of course, let me just mention, when I say ZZ,
it's shorthand for Z tensor Z. And so
on for all of these others.
Do you also negation of all of the properties
in the [INAUDIBLE]?
Like for instance, you could also
have this be like the minus IZ.
Good question.
So instead of answering your question
about what about the negation, suppose I have the state--
let's say 011.
What is going to stabilize this?
Well, it's a plus 1 eigenstate of Z1
and a minus 1 eigenstate of Z2 and Z3.
And so to be a stabilizer, I need to be a plus 1 eigenstate.
So one of the stabilizers is ZII.
But for the second qubit, the stabilizer I want is minus IZI.
And the third qubit, it's minus--
oops.
Minus IIZ.
So when I put a minus sign here, remember the way these enter in
is that v sub s should be a plus 1 eigenstate of this operator.
So if I put in a minus sign, that's
like saying that it should be a minus I
eigenstate of the operator before I put in the minus sign.
So it definitely changes things to put in the minus sign.
And of course, if I put in both a poly and its negated version
together, then [INAUDIBLE] these issues about y's,
I would get minus identity, and so then nothing
would be allowed, which is kind of like saying
that a qubit can't be both 0 and 1.
Good.
Any other questions so far?
So these are all one-dimensional subspaces.
Of course, we also saw, for the repetition code,
it had these stabilizers.
So for the repetition code, you want to add the constraint that
the first two qubits are equal in the 01 basis and the second
two qubits are equal.
So how do you impose that two qubits are equal?
You say that they're stabilized by a product of z's on both
of those qubits.
Because those will-- that's basically
checking the XOR of those two bits
and verifying that the XOR is equal to 0.
So I checked that.
The first two qubits are the same,
and the second and third qubit are the same.
What if I want this code, the span of plus, plus, plus,
and minus, minus, minus?
What would the stabilizer group be for these?
Right.
It's XXI.
And then what's the other one?
IXX.
So we're doing the same thing, except instead of the 01 basis,
we have the plus minus basis.
And on that basis, the x operator just looks the same--
acts the same way the z operator does.
Plus is a plus 1 eigenstate.
Minus is a minus 1 eigenstate.
And you'll notice one thing about this,
which is for the first examples where
I had a one-dimensional subspace,
I had as many stabilizer generators as I had qubits.
And basically, that's because every stabilizer generator
is like a constraint.
If you take a poly, then half of its eigenvalues are plus 1.
Half of its eigenvalues are minus 1.
And if I constrain myself to be in the plus 1 eigenspace,
then that's sort of cutting me down to half of the space.
So in general, I start with 2 to the n dimensions.
And every time I impose a stabilizer constraint,
I'm cutting my dimensions in half.
So if I have as many stabilizers as qubits,
I've cut myself down to one dimension.
Here, I start with eight dimensions.
And I only put in two stabilizers.
So I've divided by 4.
I'm still left with two dimensions.
And we'll see in a minute that's a more general phenomenon.
With a big asterisk, which is, these
have to be non-redundant stabilizers.
So these are non-redundant.
I can't multiply them together to get the identity.
But if I were to add a third stabilizer, like ZIZ,
that would be redundant.
That wouldn't carry any more information.
It wouldn't further change the subspace
or cut down its dimension.
And I should say this is kind of a non-trivial fact,
that each one will cut down the dimensions by half.
You shouldn't necessarily believe me right away.
I'll prove it in a minute.
But it's not at all obvious.
Just because each poly by itself has
1/2 plus 1 eigenvalues and 1/2 minus 1 eigenvalues,
it doesn't follow that when you combine
two of them, the fraction--
they keep on being sort of unbiased relative
to each other.
It's like saying if I flip many coins,
each one is heads half the time and tails half the time,
regardless of the previous coin flips.
That's true of coins, but it doesn't
have to be true of operators.
It could have been that if the first three polys I checked,
I'm in the plus 1 eigenstate of those,
the next one is more likely to be in the plus 1 eigenspace.
That turns out not to be true, but a priori
it's possible when I'm just dealing
with arbitrary matrices.
So there's, again, something special about polys
that they have this property.
I'll give one more example, which I won't
give a full derivation of.
So suppose that VS is the code space of the shor
nine qubit code.
So this belongs in the space subset
of a two-dimensional subset of the space of nine qubits.
So I'll write down--
so if you remember this one, this
was the concatenation of these two codes.
So we would take plus plus plus and minus minus minus,
and then encode each of these in turn
into this three-bit repetition code.
So at the lowest level, you have a regular three-bit repetition
code, and you have three of them.
So you want to enforce all of those constraints.
So for example--
I'm going to use different notation instead of the ZZ III,
since I don't want to write a ton of I's.
I'll just say Z1 Z2 means product of the first two polys,
identity on the rest.
Z2 Z3, et cetera.
So that forces the first three qubits
to be in this code space.
Then I'll do the same thing for qubits four, five, six,
and seven, eight, nine.
So for four, five, six, I do Z4 Z5, Z5 Z6,
and then Z7 Z8, Z8 Z9.
OK, so that forces each three-qubit block
to be in a little repetition code like this.
Then the next step is something which a full justification of I
will have to give you later, but we
have to somehow ensure that the outer code block looks
like an encoded version of this plus plus
plus minus minus minus code.
And so to do that, we want to take these stabilizers
and encode them according to this inner code.
And the way that looks is, they turn into--
they were sort of two X operators.
They turn into six X operators.
So it looks like X1 X2 X3 X4 X5 X6 is one of them,
and then the other one is basically four through nine.
So altogether, we have eight operators,
six products of Z's and two products of X's.
We have nine qubits all together.
So these eight operators cut us down
to a two-dimensional space.
And this is sort of offered slightly without proof,
and we'll give more justification for it later.
So these are some examples of what's possible.
Any questions about the examples,
or about the stabilizer codes more generally?
One thing I want to mention about them
is that they're a good way of defining codes,
but code is just a subspace with maybe some nice properties.
And you can really just use them to describe
a state or a subspace more generally.
You could consider that to be a code.
Sometimes these make good codes.
But in some cases, it's useful just
to describe a state without getting into
whether or not it corresponds to an error correcting code.