The criteria for when it is possible to do a quantum
error correction or not is a set of algebraic equations.
And these are also known as MacLean-Laflamme equations
after Manny Neil and Raymond Laflamme, who
first documented them and wrote them
and described in a very beautiful way.
And what I'm going to do is to present the criteria to you
and explain why they exist in a more distilled way
than you'll find in the original paper,
building on just the limited scenario that we have described
in this course.
So here's the setting.
We have a channel between our two famous people, Alice
and Bob.
So this is the message that Bob receives
over a noisy channel, E. And we can write it,
in general, as this form of E sub k, Ro, E sub k, dagger.
You've only seen this in limited cases
where these E's are unitary.
For example, identity or X or Z for the bit flip and the phase
flip channel.
And in those cases, there is some probability
attached to them.
So there's 1 minus p.
So we have 1 minus P times identity or P times x.
So you know that these are not unitary operators, but rather
shrunken unitary operators at the very least,
like P times X. It turns out that all you need to do
is to have a set of operators which satisfy
the fact that the sum of E sub k, dagger E sub k,
is equal to identity.
And that you don't need to have them be unitary or so forth,
but I'm not going to go through that argument about proof
today.
Given this channel, here's a theorem.
Let C be a quantum code defined by the--
remember, for it to be a quantum code,
it just has to be a subspace of a Hilbert space.
So I have to define what that subspace is, and I'll
define that by giving its basis vectors,
so as defined by the orthonormal basis.
of L.
And I claim that there exists a quantum operator recovering
So I need two things for there to be error correction.
I need to be able to show that we can measure the syndrome,
and then give a recovery operator based
on that syndrome.
And so the recovery operator here
will implicitly define the syndrome operator.
And I claim that this recovery operator corrects
some error, which will be one of these channel errors, E.
But only if and only if two conditions are met.
The first of these conditions is called
the orthogonality condition.
And that is that if I have some code where size of L,
and some error, E sub j, it should take it
to a different state than a different error applied
to the same code word.
So that this inner product is equal to zero,
prof j not equal to k, and for all code words, like so.
So the picture behind this is that I
have a Hilbert space with some code
C, that's a subspace of the Hilbert space.
And I want the channel to have error operators that
take me to Hilbert spaces which don't overlap each other.
So they go apart, like this.
C prime and C double prime.
But we don't have some operator that goes and intersects
Hilbert spaces in some way, that would be no good because we
cannot distinguish the errors from each other.
And that's fairly simple.
The second condition is called the non-deformation condition.
And that is that, mathematically,
if I have a set--
an error E sub k, acting on code words, size of L,
this should not distinguish one code word
from another code word.
So this should be all the same value, let's call this d sub k,
for all the code words.
That is, if identity did something to a qubit
and then an error, like an x error, changes it,
by a different amount, I say, because the probabilities
are different, then it's going to shrink one vector compared
with other vector.
So this is going to take a vector space that
looks like that into something that
might be a shrunken pancake.
That's no good because then you don't have a squared up Hilbert
space anymore, and so you can't correct it.
So these are the two conditions, orthogonality and
non-deformation.
And let me try to give you the proof of the statement.
The reason the proof is interesting
is because the proof is constructive.
The proof will actually tell you what the recovery operator
is going to be.
So you'll be able to see how to do it
and then you can believe that you can find
lots of error correction codes.
But what it belies is that in actual practice,
the Hilbert space has grown so large so fast
that it's actually hard to find good quantum codes just
by exhaustively searching for them.
Still, let's work through the proof
and then maybe you'll also see ways
of making them simpler on different kinds of states
that have specific patterns.
So let's define P as being the trajectory into the cold space.
I often use this as a short cut notation for density matrices.
It's not an x if this is a [INAUDIBLE]
This is the projector onto the cold space C.
And I want to note a fact here, which is useful for us
algebraically as we go through the proof, that
is if I project a given error--
two errors, so I'm going to have a state that has error Ej,
and I have another state that has error E sub
k, if I look at the overlap of this thing,
then this is going to be equal to d sub k, delta J k P
by virtue of combining these two statements over here.
So the delta comes from this, so you only
get something that's non-zero when j is not equal to k.
And you get the same thing for all code words, D sub k,
from the non-deformation condition.
So this is a restatement of the theorem
over here in one very concise mathematical statement.
Also, a beautiful fact from matrix theory
known as the polar decomposition gives us
a way of taking some strange operator, matrix operator,
and decomposing that into a part, which is a rotation,
and a part which is like a shrinking part.
And so by the polar decomposition
of this particular operator, which
is E sub k P, will take an error,
E sub k is one of the errors in this notation up here,
so it might be a bit flip or phase flip, or something else,
if Y.
I can still describe this as some unitary part
and some non-unitary part.
I'll define the unitary part as U sub k,
and the recipe for the polar decomposition
states that I just square this and take its square root.
So p E sub k, dagger, E sub k P. But by this restatement
of the theorem here, we have that this is just
the square root of d sub k times U sub k P.
So here the kk gives you a 1 for the delta function,
and then the dk moves over like that.
So this is the rotation that an arrow causes.
This is the shrinkage that the error causes,
and we continue to project it into the cold space.
So now I can give you the two parts of the theorem
by constructing the syndrome measurement.
And then the recovery operator.
So for the syndrome operation measurement,
let me define a projection into a specific rotated code space.
So the intuition is, I'm going to take the different color
spaces over here that are orthogonal to each other
because of this first condition, and I'm
going to rotate them all back into the same place.
So I take this one, I rotate it here,
I take another error operator version, I rotate it over here,
and so forth.
So they all fall on top of each other.
So that's U sub k P U sub k dagger.
This is the original cold space, and then this
is rotating it by the unitary rotation
part of each one of the errors.
And by plugging that in, I can rewrite
this in two different forms.
E sub k P over d sub k square root.
So this is taking P U sub k dagger,
so it's taking the U sub k P part over here.
Use sub k dagger, or I can take the second half of this
and it gives me U sub k P E sub k dagger
divided by d sub k square root.
OK.
Now, by this statement up here, which I'll call star,
the P sub k are orthogonal.
By this I mean that for all j not equal to k.
So two different errors instead of just the same error, P sub j
times P sub k is proportional to--
let's now just multiply this out together.
That's U sub k P E sub k, dagger, that's this term here,
taken with the U on the left-hand side
on this expression.
And then we'll take the j part over here, e sub j, P U sub j.
And then there's all over a d sub k.
But now we have from here that this
is orthogonal to each other by the same end of the theorem.
So this is equal to 0.
So the syndrome measurement is to just measure
P sub k and you obtain k.
k is just the syndrome operator.
I think we're almost done.
The recovery operator is going to be just U sub k dagger.
We take the unitary part of the error and you rotate it back.
And I claimed that this will fix what you want, fix the state.
So the recovery operator applied to some impedance matrix,
or be the sum over k of U sub k P sub k ro P sub k.
This is the syndrome measurement,
this is the unitary operator that you
apply based on the syndrome measurement, U sub k dagger.
And I'm going to work out this expression
and show that that's going to give you the result.
All I need is two lines of algebra.
For a state that's a code word state,
then U sub k dagger P sub k E j side--
so an error applied to the code word state,
then projected and then rotated, is--
if you work out the algebra, the square root of D
sub k, delta j k times the original state.
And so if you plug this back into here,
you'll find that this is equal to the sum--
I'm just going to jump to the end here.
d sub k delta jk psi, psi.
The delta, I already sum.
And it goes away.
Now, this is original state, but it shrunk by a little bit.
But this term is equal to 1 because these operators that we
had, sum over k, E sub k, dagger E sub k, is equal to identity.
So this is equal to the state the [INAUDIBLE] So that's