So let me give you some examples of quantum error correcting
codes.
So one example, because it's quantum
it generalizes classical.
So one example is any classical code
is an example of a quantum error correcting code.
We'll very soon see why it's not a satisfactory example,
but mathematically, it makes sense.
In some cases, it can be a good idea.
So let's say our classical code is some collection of 2
to the k bit strings.
The way we promote that to a quantum code
is for each one of these we take the vector
and then we take the span of all these vectors
and we get a subspace.
OK, so we have a subspace of dimension 2
to the k corresponding to this classical code.
And there are some properties of the classical code
that this quantum code will inherit.
So suppose that the classical code
has distance d, meaning it corrects
d-minus one over two errors.
Well, for a classical code, there's only one kind of error
and that's a bit flip.
And in quantum language that means an x, a pollyx.
So if it has distance d, then c can
correct the set of x's on up to d minus 1 over 2 positions.
So it's kind of like what I defined here.
Here I said, I want to find operators
that looked like identity in most positions
but an arbitrary poly on up to d-minus 1 over 2 positions.
Here I'm doing something more restricted.
I'm saying it looks like identity in most places,
but it's allowed just to be x in a few others.
I'm not allowed to put any y's or z's.
So it's a more restricted set of errors.
It's basically just the errors that we have
to worry about classically.
So that's why I'm saying it's not a completely terrible code.
It does correct some of the errors that we care about.
However, it does not--
these in general do not correct z errors.
I mean, there may be special cases
where they happen to do OK against some z errors
for some strange reason.
But in general, they will not correct z errors.
So just as an example, if you take--
you know, I said in classically, the repetition code
is the best code for error correction
if you just care about correcting errors.
If you don't care about rate, efficiency,
then you just want to correct errors,
the biggest distance you can get is with the repetition code.
But quantumly, if you take the subspace spanned by these two
vectors, it's going to do a great job
of correcting x errors.
You can see they're orthogonal and they remain orthogonal
even after I apply a bunch of x's to them.
So I satisfy the error correcting condition that way.
But the relative phase between these
will be screwed up by a z in any position.
So in fact, it makes the rate of z errors n times larger
than it used to be because if I have kind
of independent z noise in every position, now
I'm vulnerable to noise in any cubit
instead of just being vulnerable to noise in one cubit.
So it makes me in a sense more vulnerable to z errors, which
is why we have a field of quantum error correcting code,
why we can't just import all the things we
know from classical codes.