A syndrome is the pattern of measurement results
from, in the linear code case, the parity-check matrix.
And it then told you what the error actually
is, after you do some extra reverse engineering,
or mapping, from that information
back to what the error was.
So that was H times E, for the linear codes.
For error correction overall, so I'll
add a little bit of discussion about the recovery operator,
here.
There are two steps.
The first step is that measurement of the syndrome.
The second step is to apply the corresponding recovery
operator, which takes the syndrome value,
gives you back the error-free state that you hope was
the one that was transmitted.
And that's error correction.
There are no more steps in it than these two.
And so, when I give you the criteria for error correction,
I will try to evidence for you these two steps constructively,
given a code and a set of errors.
And, to illustrate that, let's go through a quick example.
Recall the 3-bit bit-flip code, where we encoded a state
as a 0000 plus b 111.
What we're going to do is to apply this syndrome measurement
circuit or operator measurement circuit using
the following operators.
And we'll define these as the syndrome operators
for that code.
The first of these is that Z1, Z2.
These are poly operators on qubits one and two,
ordering the qubits from the left to the right.
But, if you will, another way of writing this
is Z tensored Z tensored I qubit one, two, and three.
But, in this community, we try to be maximally lazy,
and so we drop as much extra notation as possible--
or "suppress" it, as people say in high-energy physics.
And so we'll just write Z Z I. OK?
So, by the way, be careful in this field.
People also go so far as dropping all the [INAUDIBLE]
and the [INAUDIBLE] and just writing down
the numbers instead.
And so sometimes I'll drop into that habit.
But this is very common.
A string of letters that look like this
is actually the tensor product of Pauli matrices.
Sometimes it's more convenient to label them with numbers.
U2 will be Z2Z3.
And this is, again, I tensored Z tensored Z, or IZZ.
And I claim that, if you measure these two
operators on that code, it will tell you enough information
to decode what the error is and thus construct an error
correction code procedure.
So let me do that by giving you a table.
So here's Bob's state after the channel.
It's that bit-flip channel which was on the board
right here before I erased it.
And we have, for example, the case of no error.
With what probability does that happen,
if we have the bit-flip channel?
Remember that the bit-flip channel was, with probability 1
minus p, nothing happens.
With probability p, you get a bit flip.
So what is the probability of having nothing happen?
1 minus p cubed?
Yes, thank you.
1 minus p cubed.
And then let us imagine that we measure U1 and then U2.
the reason I can measure U1 and U2 both is not entirely obvious
but is very important to think about for a moment.
Any suggestions?
After all, if you measure a quantum state,
normally you can't measure something else subsequent to it
or switch the order of the two measurements,
because measurements change states.
But here I claim it actually does not
matter which order I measure these two operators in.
Why?
In blue?
Because they commute.
They commute.
Yeah, so any two operators, measurement operators,
which commute, you don't care about what order
they're measured in.
And these are deliberately chosen so that they do commute.
So I'll measure U1 first, and I'll measure U2 second.
And I'd like you to tell me what those measurement results are.
And remember, this is the Z variable
that shows up in that top qubit, over here.
And there's a--
You can work it out by going through this circuit
and throwing the state in, but there's an easy way
to see what the measurement result is,
remembering that all we want to know
is whether the state is a plus-1 or a minus-1 eigenstate
of the unitary operator U. So if you will apply ZZI
to this state coming in, does it stay unchanged?
Or does it have its sign flip?
Unchanged.
And therefore the measurement result for U1 is a--?
Infinity.
Not infinity, it's infinity and beyond.
It's a plus-1 eigenstate.
And so Z is going to turn out to be, as you read over there, 0.
That's right.
OK?
OK.
And what's the result for U2?
If you apply an IZZ to this, see, if you apply III,
nothing happens to both of these.
If you apply IZZ, remember that Z acting on 0 is 0,
Z acting on 1 is minus 1.
So Z acting here gives you a minus 1.
Z acting on the third qubit gives you another minus 1.
The two signs cancel out, so then you get a plus-1 again.
So this state is a plus-1 eigenstate of U2, IZZ.
And therefore this measurement result is also 0.
OK?
So, let's try another case.
a 001 plus b 110.
This is the case when the third qubit
has had an error occur to it.
So that was a bit flip happening in the bit-flip channel.
And remember, the hypothesis is that each of the qubits
is going to see an independent and identically
distributed channel.
So there's no difference in the channel--
no memory in the channel, as well.
And that's a very important assumption.
What is the probability with which this is received by Bob?
Richard.
y minus p squared [INAUDIBLE].
Thank you.
y minus p squared times p.
Now, what are U1 and U2?
Let's try U1 first.
That is a ZZI.
Yes, please.
0?
0.
Thank you.
How about U2?
That's IZZ.
Something new, here.
Yes, please.
1.
And tell us why.
Because now only one of the things are getting flipped.
And so they keep negative 1?
Yeah!
This ZZ hits the 01.
You get one minus sign instead of 2 minus signs.
And so this has a minus sign, and here we
have a 10, and that gives you a minus sign, as well.
So this is an overall minus-1 eigenstate of ZZI.
OK.
So, forgive me as I erase this.
Let's go through another example.
Imagine that the middle bit flips.
The probability is the same.
Now let's do the eigenstates of the syndrome operators again.
What do we get for U0--
excuse me, U1?
Remember, that's ZZI.
1.
And for U2?
[INAUDIBLE]
Also 1.
Last case.
The first bit flips.
OK?
Same probability.
What's U1?
Aha.
1, and U2?
0.
Yeah.
Look at that!
Four different values of the syndrome operators,
four different states.
They also happen to be orthogonal to each other.
That's important.
We'll come back to that.
But now we can also figure out what the recovery operator
should be.
This is a unitary operation that I
apply to the state that's received,
to make it transform back into the original state that
was sent by Alice.
So, in this first case, what operator should Bob
apply, to get back to the state Alice sent?
I.
II.
I II.
You should be saying "II, I."
OK?
Second case.
What do you apply?
[INAUDIBLE]
IIX.
Or X on 3.
OK?
And then this is X on 2, and this is X on 1.
But now we have this nice little table, here.
You just read off from the syndrome that you measured.
Then you apply the recovery operator
that matches that syndrome.
Yes, please.
So, there's some probability that more than one error
occurred--
Yes!
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes.
Thus we can bound the probability of error
by saying, what happens if you have had two errors happen,
or three errors happen, and say that in all of those cases
we did the wrong thing and got the wrong result?
OK.
So that's going to be equal to 2 times--
So, instead of one error happening,
it's going to go as p squared.
Excuse me.
There are three possible cases for that-- p squared times 1
minus p, and three errors happening.
So, p cubed.
And so, if we sum that up, what we'll want to do
is to cast this probability of error
in terms of a well-known metric.
And we haven't seen this metric in the class so far,
but it's called "fidelity."
And it's defined as being this function F which
takes in a density matrix.
And, for this class, I'll define it
as being relative to a pure state,
but there are more general cases.
We'll say that this is defined as being
the overlap of the pure state with a density matrix,
like so, and the fidelity of the state that's received by Bob--
so this is the state that Bob decodes.
So this is post-Bob.
I'm not going to write it down so explicitly, there.
Let's write it down here.
So it's the recovery operator applied to the state
that Bob receives, which is E of rho,
compared with a state that Alice sent, which was psi.
And we can say that this is bounded
above by 1 minus this probability error, of error.
OK?
So this is 1 minus 3p squared plus 2p cubed.
So one p cubed from here, one taken away over here.
Good?
So, this is one of the signatures of quantum error
correction being successful, the fact that this fidelity now
goes as p squared instead of going
as p, which would be the case if you
had done no error correction.
And experimentalists seek this kind
of quadratic turnover in the fidelity, versus a linear one,