Let's look at a quantum code and use
that as an example to illustrate some
of these ideas and definitions.
Remember the quantum bit flip code.
So now in order to understand the code let's
first look at the noise model.
What I just erased here was the classical noise model
of the binary symmetric channel.
In the quantum case, what we have
is a map that says that some input density
matrix goes to sum output density matrix e of row.
This is a notation that's commonly
used in the community, which I'll
start to use today, which was with some probability 1 minus p
the original density matrix that comes in.
You can think of this as a pure state if you wish.
With some probability 1 minus p nothing happens to the state.
But I'll have a stochastic combination.
So with probability p, I'll have some error.
And in this case, the error is x row x.
And remember, we conjugate.
We put the unitary operation on both sides of a density matrix.
If this were a pure state, this would
be something like psi psi, and then it
would have u and u dagger on either side like this.
So think of that as you see a term which describes an error.
I'm not going to describe in formal ways
all the ways that a density matrix can involve,
but this is the noise model.
And this is called the bit flip channel.
And we encoded a single qubit for this code
where we defined the logical 0 as being
three zeros and the logical 1 as being three ones.
So another thing that's useful to keep in mind
is the picture behind this.
What we have is two parties that are trying to communicate.
And these are probably the two most famous people
in the field after Peter Shore, Alice and Bob.
So Alice had some state row.
And she's communicating with Bob over a channel
which I'll call e or epsilon.
And Bob receives e of row like this.
So that's the physical picture behind what I'm drawing.
Right.
And Bob wants to be able to recover the information
that Alice has sent, despite what Eve might do.
Eve being the environment that's causing the errors,
otherwise known as e or epsilon in this diagram.
So Eve is probably the fourth most famous person
in quantum information.
The way we're doing this can be defined
in a much more formal way by giving you
an analogous definition to the classical codes,
but for quantum codes.
So let me define that for you.
A quantum code with parameters n, k, and d.
Excuse me.
I'm going to leave out distances for now.
So a quantum n, k code--
and the convention in the community
is to use double brackets for quantum
codes versus single brackets for classical codes--
is defined as a k qubit subspace of an n qubit Hilbert space.
Period.
There's no more to the definition.
That is, it's just some subspace of a Hilbert space.
Just like for classical codes I told you
the classical code was a set of bit strings.
Now, OK, it's a subspace instead of just a set of vectors.
But the set of vectors happens to be orthonormal to each other
and defines a Hilbert subspace.
So the reason I've left out distances and so forth
is because they're a little hard to define
until I give you the analogous quantity to a Hamming weight
and Hamming distance.
And I'm not going to do that in this class.
But you can rest assure that it does exist
and is a very powerful thing in the field.
So let's get an example.
Again, 0 0 0 and 1 1 1 is the logical codewords.
Here are k equals 1, n equals 3.
Now, compare this with what you might
do if you are a classical coding theorist in 1995.
You might have said if Alice has stated
that she wants to transmit row, then
she should transmit psi, psi, psi.
Why can't she do that?
Well, if she doesn't know how to produce psi
but she was just giving it, then, first of all,
she has no way to clone that unknown state
to get three copies of it.
Secondly, you'll find that even if you did create it and send
it across like this, you can't measure that state to find out
what errors occurred on it.
So although we showed you how this works,
there is an enormous conceptual leap
that went to creating this instead of that
that I want you to appreciate.
And this is not how quantum codes work.
This is how quantum codes work.
This is the obvious way to make quantum codes
that we've just forgotten about because it doesn't work.
And there is something very non-intuitive about doing it
this way until you get your mind rearranged like a quantum