So what happens if you apply 1, 0, 0 e to the i theta
to one of these qubits.
Let's say 2 qubit 2.
OK.
Well, 0 goes to 1/2, 0, 0, 0 plus 0, 1, 1 plus e
to the i theta 0, 1, 1 plus 1, 0, 1 plus e to the i
theta 1, 1, 0.
1 goes to 1/2, 0, 0, 0.
I'm not doing this right.
0, 0, 1 plus e to the i theta 0, 1, 0 plus 1,
0, 0 plus e to the i theta 1, 1, 1.
So now, what we want to do is we want
to project these states onto 0, logical 0,
logical 1 and logical--
OK, so we made the phase error on the second qubit.
So let's call this sigma z on a second qubit, logical zero
and sigma z on the second qubit, logical 1.
So these are the only things that
are going to get projected onto because--
we can-- suppose we try projecting this on to sigma z
error on the third qubit.
You would get 0, 0, 1 minus--
or rather you get minus 0, 0, 1 plus 1, 0, 0.
So that's minus 1 plus 1.
And here you get e to the i theta minus e to the i theta.
So this state is orthogonal to sigma z, 1, 0, 0l, et cetera.
And it turns out that--
let's see.
How much time do I have?
OK, I was going to do this projection.
But maybe I'll just skip this math
and go on to the easy way of seeing this.
So the easy way of seeing this is 1, 0, 0,
e to the i theta is equal to e to the i theta over 2, e
to the minus i theta, 0, 0, e to the i theta is
equal to e to the i theta cos theta times
I minus e to the i theta 2.
Yeah, these should have thetas over 2's on them.
Sine theta over 2, sigma z because e to the i theta over 2
is cos theta over 2 plus i sine theta over 2.
So I left out an i here.
So maybe it's useful doing this projection.
So let's project this state.
Project 1, e to the i theta on 2, sigma z on 2.
This is on qubit 2.
Yeah.
2, a logical 1, which is 0, 0, 1 minus 0, 1, 0 plus 1,
0, 0 minus 1, 1, 1, to 1/2.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to take the inner product sigma z 2.
OK, we really should be projecting onto a subspace.
So let's project it onto this subspace formed
by sigma z error on the second qubit of the original code
space.
So an error-correcting code is a subspace of Hilbert space.
So we'll project this onto the subspace
you get by applying a sigma z to the second qubit.
So we get the projection 1/2 times 1/2--
that's 1/4-- minus e to the i theta--
again, I guess we divide by 4--
plus 1/4 again minus e to the i theta over 4
is equal to 1/4 times 1 minus e to the i theta over 2.
Now, if you project 1, e to the i theta,
0l onto the same subspace, you get the same amplitude except--
OK, I'm doing this wrong.
This is a sigma z 2 error applied to a 1.
If you project the small-phase error applied to a 0 onto
the same subspace, you're going to get the same thing--
sigma z 2 error applied to 0.
So basically that takes this and, with some probability,
projects it onto this subspace and, with the 1
minus that probability, projects it onto the correct space.
And the reason this works is that you
can write this as that.
And with this probability, when you apply this to that state,
gets projected onto the correct encoded qubit.
And with this probability, it gets
projected onto the encoded qubit with 1 sigma z error
on the second qubit.
I don't know.
Was this too complicated?
And the reason that works is that your actual error
can be expressed as e to the i theta over 2
cosine theta over 2 times no error minus this times
a sigma z error on the second qubit.
And then, when you measure it, the way the code works
is that cos theta over 2 squared of the time.
You will measure that there was no error.
And when you do that, the code with the error
gets projected onto the no error subspace.
And sine theta over 2 squared of the time,
you will measure that there was an error.
And when you do that, its gets projected
onto the code subspace with an error on the second qubit.
Now you know which one it got projected onto.
You can fix the error on the second qubit.
OK, so we can go back here.
Any 2 by 2 matrix is alpha i times sigma times
i plus alpha x, sigma x plus alpha y, sigma y plus alpha
z, sigma z.
So any 2 by 2 matrix can be expressed
as in the Pauli basis.
So a sigma x error, a sigma y error, and a signal z error,
which means any error on one qubit is, I guess,
superpositioned of these.
And that means, if you can fix any error on a single qubit
of the flavor sigma x, sigma y, sigma z,
you can fix any one-qubit error.
For example, measure qubit in 0, 1 basis.
If you measure 0, it corresponds to 1, 0, 0, 0.
So that corresponds to projecting that qubit
onto the 0 qubit, which, of course, is equal to 1 1
plus 1/2, 1, minus 1.
So if you measure a qubit and you
get 0, half the time, when you try to correct it,
you will get there was no error.
And the other half, you will get there was a sigma z error.
And similarly, if you got 1, you would
get exactly the same thing.
Half the time, you would get no error.
And half the time, you would get the sigma z error.
So that is how this quantum error correcting code
will protect against any error in a single qubit.
Now, there are codes that protect
against t errors of the form sigma x, signal y, or sigma z.
And those will protect against any error
on any subset of t qubits.
And these codes are the ones that
can be used to transmit information reliably.