We want to talk about code transformations.
So we want unitaries such that UP U dagger, if P is a poly,
then UP U dagger should also be a poly for all polys P.
And so I'm interested in--
I want to know about the set of these U's.
And this set is called the Clifford group.
So it's the set of U--
I can write this line a little more compactly--
as U Pn U dagger is contained in Pn.
So Pn is a set of polys.
If I conjugate them by U, I should
remain within the set of polys.
In fact, this conjugation does not destroy information.
So I could replace this with an equal sign,
and it would mean the same thing.
So the first thing I want to do is talk
about what's in the Cliffords.
And then we'll talk about how they act on polys
in this vector space language.
Is it clear what I mean by the definition of the Clifford
group?
OK, so let's try to find what the elements of it are.
The first thing as we start to populate it is we
can certainly put all of the polys inside of it,
because the polys form a group.
So if I have an element of the polys
and I conjugate them by another poly,
I get back yet another poly.
So one easy thing I can put in it are the other polys.
But that's not all.
There are also non-polys that are
in this group that nevertheless will map polys to polys.
So one example of this is the Hadamard gate.
So Hadamard-- assuming you've seen it in 8.370--
is this matrix.
Actually, I used it earlier in the class, even.
So it has these properties.
I guess I'm not writing the dagger,
because it's equal to its own dagger.
And so right away, we see that this maps polys to polys
when I conjugate.
So all of the Hadamards belong to the Clifford group.
So let me write H1 through Hn belong to the Clifford group,
where Hi means Hadamard acting on the i-th position.
So this is a single qubit gate that's not a poly.
Nevertheless, it's in the Clifford group.
Another example is the phase gate.
So let me define S to be the square root of Z.
And I guess, it's a little ambiguous what
square roots mean, but I'll take the one that looks like 1,
0, 0, i.
And I claim--
I could also write this as e to the i pi over 4 z--
or pi over 2?
Pi over 4, yeah, pi over 4.
So I claim that this is also in the Clifford group.
So why is that?
Well, if you put a Z here, it's just
going to compute with that.
So you're going to get back the Z. Then it's definitely a poly.
What about if you put an X-- if you do SX S dagger?
So here, these do not commute, and S is not a poly.
So they don't anti-commute either.
So if I try to move the S past the X,
I'm not going to just pick up a minus sign.
So you have to be a little bit careful here.
However, if I write it in this way, then the z in the exponent
does pick up a minus sign.
So I can write this as X e to the minus i pi over 4
z times S dagger, because as I move the e to the i
pi over 4 z past it, the z in the exponent
picks of a minus sign.
And so what's this equal to-- e to the minus i pi over 4 times
z?
That's equal to S dagger.
So this is equal to X S dagger S dagger.
What's S dagger squared?
Z. So this equal to XZ belongs to the poly group.
Good.
Now, this argument can only really
rely on it being a square root.
So one gate which is useful in quantum computing
is the T gate, which is the square root of S.
So I'm going to define it to be 1, 0, 0, e to the i pi over 4.
There's a few different ways of defining it.
I can vary the overall phase.
So this is e to the i--
Yeah, that is--
So this is e to the i pi over 8 times z.
And it turns out if you do TX T dagger,
the same argument will give you X S dagger.
You move the T past this, it becomes T dagger.
And so this is not in the poly group.
So you can't just put any phase you like on the diagonal.
It's really only specific values that will work.
And it turns out--
this is not--
I don't know a very easy way of proving this, other than kind
of checking a lot of cases--
that the single-qubit Cliffords--
actually, I guess it will follow from things
that we'll show later.
But I don't know a totally self-contained way of doing it.
The single-qubit Cliffords, it turns out,
are generated by the polys, Hadamard, and the phase gate.
In fact, I didn't really need the polys in here,
because if I take S squared, I get Z. And with Z and H,
I can get back the--
can get X. So really, just Hadamard and S
are enough to generate the single-qubit Cliffords.
So these examples I've given, I claim
that's all there is for first single qubits.