What happens when you apply unitaries to density matrices?
Ensemble psi of i with probability p of i.
Apply u and you get u psi of i with probability p of i.
And the density matrix here was row
equals summation p of i psi psi.
And the density matrix here is going
to be rho tilda equals sum p of i.
Well, we now have u psi of i instead of psi of i.
So u psi of i, and now psi of i u dagger.
Well, again, we use linearity.
And this is just summation.
p of i-- wait.
No.
What we want to do is we want to move
the u outside the summation.
So this gives u summation p of i psi of i,
or rather the projection onto psi of i, u dagger.
But this is row.
Equals u row u dagger.
So you apply a unitary to a density matrix,
you get u row u dagger.