Let me talk about the space of errors
that you might want to correct.
In classical codes, in principle,
you could consider any set of allowable errors.
But for simplicity, especially if we
want a good theoretical description of them,
we start by saying let's just talk about the number of--
let's describe errors in terms of how many bits they affect.
So let's do the same thing for qubits.
Let's say I want to code the correct errors
on up to 2 qubits or up to 17 up to some number of qubits
So these are called low-weight errors.
And so one typical choice of error
set s is the set of errors on, let's say, l
equals d minus 1 over 2 qubits.
So I could say errors on up to--
I should say up to l qubits.
That's the number I'm introducing.
It'll be convenient.
Remember, in the classical case, this
is corresponding to a distance.
I said, if you have distance d, you
can correct d minus 1 over 2 errors.
So we'll do the same thing in the quantum case.
We'll set l equal to some number d minus 1 over 2.
So what does that mean in the quantum case?
This has to be a linear subspace,
so this would be the span of some operators.
And one way of doing this is to say,
let's just consider our errors.
Let's expand our areas in the polybasis.
And so this will be--
if you want a basis for all operators on n qubits,
you can write it as a tensor product
of a poly on the first qubit, poly on the second qubit,
and so on.
We could also just write this as sigma p vector
where p vector is a vector of length n with entries
that are 0, 1, 2, and 3.
So 1, 2, 3 correspond to the x, y, and z polys.
0 corresponds to the identity.
Oh, sorry, and this should be such
that the number of nonzero entries of p is at most l.
So the number of non-zero entries
is the number of positions where you have a non-identity poly.
So these are polys where most of the positions are identity,
but in up to all other places you can put x, y, or z.
And I should emphasize that there's nothing special
about polys here.
Polys are just a nice basis for operators.
I could also write this as the span of operators A1
through An where these are now totally general matrices.
But I have the condition that at most, lai
are not equal to the identity.
So most of these, again, should be identity.
This poly picture is a very convenient and common one
to use, and it's a very good one to use.
But the risk is that it gives you the misleading impression
that errors are unitary.
And you saw in the problem set this amplitude damping noise,
which is a very common type of physical noise you cannot
describe it as a mixture of unitaries,
and so we have to be able to correct this type of error.
However, the polys are also a spanning set.
And so we can always expand any kind of noise
as a linear combination of unitaries,
and that will still be true mathematically.
And because of this property, that if I correct,
the set of errors I can correct is a linear subspace,
if I can correct--
it's efficient to correct polys up to weight l.
And that will cover any operator that is not
identity on up to l positions.
So there is something without loss of generality
about the polys that does not mean
that noise is always unitary.
This is because of the linearity of error-correcting codes,
let us get away with thinking about things
in terms of unitary errors.
Of course, it could be more efficient
if you have amplitude damping noise,
just design your code for that.
And then you really don't want to think in terms of polys.
But initially, we will just talk about poly errors
and about noise that effects up to some number of qubits.
So if this happens--
so I should say if we correct errors in s,
then we say that the code has distance d.
And this is really just by analogy
with the classical situation, all right?
I cannot talk.
I could try to--
there are ways of talking about codewords being distance
d apart of [INAUDIBLE] weight.
But that's rather contrived.
It's really just saying a classical coded distance
d can correct d minus 1 over 2 errors.
So we just sort of go the other way quantitatively.
We can say if you can correct d minus 1 over 2 errors,
then that means that we say that you have distance
d because we're very used to saying a distance 3 code can
correct 1 error.