These, you can see already are gonna
define a class of code transformations.
So if I act with H, for example, I turn these into X's.
And this is something we already found
useful in talking about the nine qubit shore code.
It was useful to turn the 3-bit repetition code, whose
stabilizers were Z1Z2 and Z2 Z3 into a code that was repetition
in a different basis, where the stabilizers were X1X2 and X2X3.
That was just done by transforming with the Hadamard.
And s will also give us code transformations
that are of that nature.
Where you're really just rotating
the single qubit bases.
And actually, already you can see
it will change the error correcting properties.
So if I have a code that corrects a z error,
and I do a Hadamard, it will instead correct an x error.
So there can be some kind of non-trivial changes there.
But these are limited, of course,
in that they're single cubic gates.
So they're not going to do any kind of entangling
transformation.
And, in particular, it's not going
to make things look like the trivial code.
Because, in the trivial code, the first and midas k qubits
are not entangled with the rest.
But with a general code, things should all be entangled.
For single qubits, this is all there is.
But we know that end qubit Clifford group does not just
look like tensor copies of the single qubit.
There have to be more gates in there, entangling gates.
So let's try and, as we move beyond single qubit Clifford,
let's try and think of some more examples.
So one example, which is maybe a little unsatisfactory,
is the swap gate.
So if I have a string of polies and I conjugate it by swap,
it will just swap the polies in positions i and j.
So that's gonna map any poly to another poly.
And this is a funny gate, because, in some ways
it can create entanglement.
If I have, well, depending on how you define entanglement,
it can be used to create entanglement.
But if I start with a totally product state,
it will not map that to non-product state.
So this alone will, again, not take us to the trivial code.
There's one more transformation we need.
And this is, I think, what makes the Clifford
group so non-trivial and interesting,
and that is the control knot
Turns out, the control knot is also
a member of the Clifford group.
And let me let me try to argue this with pictures.
So suppose we have, so you know this
is what a c-knot looks like.
We do a c-knot.
Then we do an x and then another c-knot.
C-knot is equal to its own dagger,
so I don't need to put the dagger in here.
What does this mean?
I look at the first bit, if it's set to one,
I flip the second bit.
Then I do an x and I do another c-knot.
So what we find is that if the first bit was zero,
sorry the first was originally one,
then it'll do a bit flip down here.
Then it will get set to zero, and then it will knot act.
Or if it was zero, it won't do a bit flip here,
but it will do one here.
Either way, the second bit gets flipped exactly once.
So this is just equal to doing an x on both lines.
So in equations, what this means is
that c-knot i j x i and c-knot i j dagger is equal to x j.
And, in fact, we can make a little table.
So let's just actually call the qubits one and two.
So if you keep doing this calculation
for each of these four.
Let's look at c-knot one two, p c-knot one two dagger.
Then so x1 gets mapped to x1 x2.
It turns out x2 gets left alone.
Because if I have a x on this line,
it just commutes with the c-knot.
Z1 one on the first line, what would
happen to z1 if I conjugate it by controlled knot.
Nothing, right, z1 just commutes with controlled knot.
And then this last one is a little bit not obvious,
but it turns out that a z2 will kind of move
backwards through a c-knot.
This kind of had to be true to preserve the commutation
relations.
You can also see it by direct calculation
or by using the fact that if you had
a margin on both sides of a c-knot,
it reverses the direction of the c-knot.
So the key takeaway is that these
are all in the poly group.
So that means that the c-knot is also an element
of the Clifford's.
And, again, I claim that this is it.
I mean there are things you can get
by multiplying these together, but this generates everything.
So I claim that the end qubit Clifford's are
generated by the Hadamard phases and c-knots.
Just these are enough to generate the entire Clifford.
So these are the set of transformations
of unitary transformations that will take polies
to other polies.
And therefore, they will take stabilizer codes
to other stabilizer codes.
And I've described everything in kind of a group notation.
Next time, I'm going to talk about it in vector language.
And so we can see some justification of this fact
that whatever the inner products are,
there's some transformation that will take you