Partial trace on density matrix rho is--
well, you can do the same thing as representing--
let's call this trace A psi, psi, A, B.
And I really should have done this, because you can only
apply partial traces to density matrices, and not pure states,
formally, although is summation from i e sub i, rho e sub i.
And rho is on a bipartite system,
and e sub i's are only for the first [INAUDIBLE]..
So here, we have a formula for the trace
which uses some basis for the first system.
So suppose you have two bases for the first system.
We have two bases for system a, e sub i and f sub i--
Well, if you have two bases for the same system,
there is a unitary matrix, which takes one basis to the other.
And we can assume that e sub j is equal to sum ujk f sub k,
where ujk, u are the elements of a unitary matrix.
So we have a unitary matrix taking e's taking, I guess,
f's to the e's.
And now, summation j, ej, rho ej is equal to summation.
k summation k prime f sub k ujk dagger rho f sub k prime,
ujk prime.
And that is equal to--
I left out the summation for j, so we put it back in.
Well, let's put summation for j inside,
and we have k k prime summation ujk dagger ujk prime
f sub k rho fk prime.
Now, this is equal to sum k k prime fk rho fk prime,
which is just this formula, where the e is replaced
by the f's.
And why is this?
ujk is a unitary matrix, which means
any two different rows are orthogonal
and the inner product of rho with itself is 1.
And this is just the inner product
of a row k with row k prime.
Wait, am I saying rows when I should be saying columns?
Let's see, jk.
Yeah, this is just the inner product
of column k with column k prime.
And that means that if k equals k prime, then this is 1.
If k is different from k prime, it's
0, which gives you the Kronecker delta, function,
which gives you that.
So it doesn't matter which bases for system
that you use in this formula, you get the same partial trace.
And why is it called partial trace?
Trace of psi a, or rather, suppose
you have two different matrices, sigma sub a tensor sigma sub b
is equal to trace sigma a times sigma b.
So if you have a tensor product of two matrices,
the partial trace just takes the trace of the first one.
And if you have something that's not the tensor product of two
matrices, you can break it up into a sum
of tensor products of the two matrices and use this formula.
So this is why it's called partial trace,
because it's just the, I guess, linearization of the operator
trace of sigma a times sigma b.