OK, one left, complete positivity.
Let's suppose that rho is positive semdefinite.
Then I can write rho in the form W W dagger.
Remember, PSD has these three equivalent conditions.
This is the one that people usually don't talk about.
Every so often, it comes in handy.
So now, what's N of rho--
sorry.
N tensor identity of rho is sum over e,
Ve tensor identity W W dagger Ve dagger tensor identity.
So it looks like a mess until you realize there's a pattern.
This operator here is the dagger of that operator there.
So I can write this, if I call this thing, let's say, Xe,
this is just sum over e, Xe Xe dagger.
So what do I know about Xe Xe dagger?
Is it positive semidefinite, for example?
Right.
This also satisfies that condition,
and the sum of [? PSD ?] things is also [? PSD. ?] So this is
a [? PSD ?] matrix.
So we've satisfied the trace preserving,
and now the completely positive conditions.
I mean, this shouldn't surprise us
because we derived Kraus operators in a way
where they should have preserved the set of density matrices.
This is just a more direct way of seeing it.
And this gives you one direction of the equivalents
So I said that trace preserving TPCP
maps have Kraus decompositions.
I just showed you the opposite, or the converse [INAUDIBLE]..
If you have a Kraus decomposition,
then you are a TPCP map.
So the other direction is the one
that will actually prove this claim of completeness
that I said.
That channels with Kraus decompositions
are all there is.