This is a very important fact about quantum error correction.
In the early days of quantum computing
after short factoring algorithm came out,
there were arguments on--
this may show my age-- but there's
something called Usenet, which was like an early Twitter you
could say.
And there were arguments on Usenet
about whether quantum computers could ever
be realized because of noise.
They said well, these look very powerful,
but we've already known that in-theory analog computers are
very powerful.
These amplitudes of quantum computers,
they just look like the real numbers
that you see in analog quantum computers.
And so we should maybe not be surprised
that this model is more powerful.
But we know that analog computers cannot be realized
at least not to very high precision
because if the voltage--
if all of the voltages are legal values, right--
in a digital computer, it's either 0 volts or 5 volts.
Everything else is illegal.
So if the computer sees 4.9, it knows
it should bump it up to five.
But in analog computer, if 3.7 is legal,
a legal voltage, and 3.700001 is also legal voltage,
there's nothing the computer can do
to know if there's a little drift of voltage,
if that was supposed to happen, or if it is something
that should be corrected.
So analog computing is fundamentally not
error correctable.
In some cases that's OK.
If your stereo doesn't produce exactly the right sound then
that's fine.
But if you want to use these real numbers
for some complicated math calculation, it's not so good.
And so there was that argument given
that quantum computers suffered the same limitation
as analog computers, namely you can not
error correct amplitudes.
And indeed, if you have some error that looks like e
to the i faded z--
and it just is in notation by the way.
Let me-- I'm going to write x equals sigma
x, y equals sigma y z.
From now on, I'm going to use this kind of quantum computing
notation for the Pauli matrices.
So I find this error, e to the i fade to z.
Data can continuously vary.
It could be very, very small.
You know, I can't distinguish all those different errors,
so how can I correct them?
That was a compelling argument against quantum computers
before quantum error correcting codes came along.
And I think [INAUDIBLE] used that discussion that
was part of what pushed Peter Schorr and others to develop
quantum error correcting codes.
And the answer we have today is that e to the i fade to z
is a linear combination of i and z.
And so if I have a code that can correct i and z,
then I can also correct at no extra cost
all linear combinations of them.
So I can correct e to the i fade to z for all values of z.
So it's a remarkable and crucial feature of quantum error action
that the space of errors they corrected is a linear subspace.