So what if you have a depolarizing channel?
What's going on is each qubit is getting taken to--
is 1 minus p, you get an i.
The probability p over 3, you get a sigma x.
Probability p over 3, you get a sigma y.
And probability p over 3, you get a sigma z.
So what you can do is 1 minus p cubed, you get i, i, i.
1 minus p squared p, you get i over 3.
You get ii sigma x, ii sigma y, ii sigma z, i
sigma x i sigma xii, et cetera.
So with probability 1 minus p squared times p over 3,
you get each of these things.
So suppose you have n cubics depolarizing channel.
Well, you can use classical probability theory
to say that with high probability, no more than pn
plus o of square root of n have errors.
So if you can fix this number of qubits,
then you can send quantum information
with high fidelity over a depolarizing channel.