So the next section is on quantum error correction,
and we'll tell you how to construct quantum
error correcting codes and how to analyze how well they work.
And for that, we need noisy quantum systems.
So you remember from last time, I
talked about classical channels and classical error
correcting codes and Shannon's theorem.
And Shannon's theorem, binary symmetric, 1 minus p, p, p,
1 minus p.
We had binary symmetric channels.
And so if you stuck in a 1 with probability p, it came out a 0.
And with probability 1, it comes out a 1.
If you stick out a 0 with probability 1 minus p,
it comes at as 0.
With probability p, it comes out with a 1.
And we can ask, is there a quantum equivalent?
And the answer is yes.
And at the end of the lecture, I hope
to get to tell you what this is.
But first, we need to construct something first.
What is a noisy quantum state?
A noisy quantum state.
Well, you can ask what's a noisy classical state?
And the answer is, a noisy classical bit
might be 0 99% of the time and 1 1% of the time.
So it's some probability distribution
over values of the bit.
Noisy classical.
And this is the model used for analyzing
noisy classical channels and classical error
correcting codes.
And so we could try doing this.
So suppose you have a state.
You have a quantum state, which is
psi of i side with probability p of i.
And in one of your early problems sets,
we actually looked at this.
Well, that's one definition of a noisy quantum state,
but it's easier to use something called density matrices.
So what this is called, this is an ensemble of quantum states.
So what is a density matrix, and why can we
use a density matrix rather than an ensemble of quantum states?
So corresponding to an ensemble of quantum states,
we get a density matrix.
Density matrix.
And the definition of a density matrix is row
equals summation p of i, psi by i, psi of i.