There's another channel.
I'd like to discuss--
the depolarizing channel.
Rho goes to rho plus--
actually, let's make it 1 minus p rho plus p over 3 sigma
x rho sigma plus p over 3 sigma y rho sigma y plus p over 3
sigma z rho sigma z.
So with 1 minus p, you do nothing.
You apply the identity matrix.
Probability of p over 3, you apply each of the three Pauli
matrices.
So is there an easier formula for this?
Yeah.
Rho goes to, I guess, 1 minus 4/3 p rho plus identity.
And the reason for this is--
Why?
For any density matrix, rho plus sigma x rho sigma x plus sigma
y rho sigma y plus sigma z rho sigma z equals--
OK, so this is completely unnormalized.
So we want this to be I over 2.
And we want this to be 1/4.
So with probability 1/4, we do nothing.
And probability 1/4, we apply sigma x.
1/4, we apply segment y.
1/4, we apply sigma z.
We get I over 2.
Proof-- well, let's call this thing sigma.
No, sigma is a bad--
Let's do tau.
Sigma x tau sigma x equals sigma y tau sigma y equals
sigma z tau sigma z equals tau.
Why is that?
Well, if we multiply this by sigma y in front and sigma y
behind, this gets taken to this sigma y.
This gets taken to rho.
Sigma x rho sigma x gets taken to sigma z rho signal z.
And this gets taken to this.
So it's invariant.
So this is true of tau.
And now the only density matrix tau which has this property
is I over 2.
OK, because let's say tau equals a, b, c, d.
Sigma x tau sigma x equals b, d, a, c.
So a has to be equal to b.
Sigma z tau sigma z equals a minus c minus d b.