So I've encoded one qubit into this code.
I can act on it by doing these five X and five Z operators.
And by the way, this should give you
a hint of why it's possible to protect quantum data in a code
and still act on it with your quantum computer.
Because in order to actually manipulate
the logical information, I need to hit all five qubits.
Let's say I want to do a logical Z or a logical X.
I need to do X or Z to all five qubits.
I can do that on my quantum computer.
I could just, in parallel, shine a laser beam on each ion,
for example.
Or send a microwave pulse in parallel
to each superconducting qubit.
But the environment is unlikely to coordinate in this way.
So this is kind of why I can use a quantum error-correcting code
and still manipulate the information while it
gets protected from error.
Or so I claim it's protected from error.
I haven't actually demonstrated that yet.
So let me now justify that.
So when we talk about error correction of the five qubit
code.
So I claim that each single qubit Pauli error
leads to a distinct syndrome.
And what I mean by syndrome is I'm given some state
Psi which is in the code space.
Some noise happens, and it gets mapped to a mixed state Rho.
And then I measure these four stabilizer generators.
So let me just call these little S1, little S2, little S3,
little S4.
And I obtain outcomes.
Let's say minus 1 to the B1, through minus 1
to the B4, where B1 through B4 are in 0, 1.
This B1 through B4, I'm calling the syndrome.
Just like for linear code, classically we
do these parity checks that tell us
whether we're in the code space or out of the code space.
Here we measure the stabilizers.
If we're in the code space all of them
will be plus one eigenstates.
So here I can say, this is minus 1 to the 0 or 1.
Then all of these B1 through B4 would be 0.
So no error means that B is equal to 0000.
And it's not a priori obvious but I
claim that any error will lead to B being
not only non-zero but even distinct for different errors.
So I claim different errors lead to distinct non-zero B.
So before I justify this, let me try and argue why
that is the right thing to do.
Why do I care that these give non-zero B
or that they are distinct?
Well, actually, let me do it in the other order.
Let me prove this is true and then we'll
talk about why it's important.
Let me actually analyze a slightly different protocol.
Suppose we also measure S5, which is a product of S1
through S4.
In other words, it's this final line here.
Of course, the outcome B5 will just B1 plus B4, mod 2.
You know, I can interpret these as elements of F2.
Because there is no extra information here--
these are commuting operators-- so once I've
measured these four, I'm in a simultaneous eigenstate
of the four of them, I'm not going
to get any extra information from S5.
So I can sort of assume that I've measured it
without loss of generality.
It adds or takes away nothing.
The only reason to do it is it makes the analysis
of what I'm writing down a little bit cleaner
and a little more symmetric.
OK, so, with that out of the way,
let's look at what happens when we have a single qubit error.
So suppose the error is X1.
So the state is X1 times Psi.
What is the syndrome going to be?
So in other words, when we measure these stabilizers,
when are we going to get plus 1, when are we going at minus 1?
If there is no error, then we're in the code space.
All of them are plus 1.
But this X1 commutes with some of the stabilizers
and anti-commutes with others.
And so, what happens is, if it commutes with the stabilizer,
it leaves a plus 1 eigenstate of that stabilizer.
But if it anti-commutes it flips it to minus 1.
So to figure out the syndrome, we
need to figure out which one of these
it commutes and anti-commutes with.
So let's go through.
For S1, what does it do, commute or anti-commute?
[INAUDIBLE]
What's that?
Anti-commute.
Why is that?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
You just look at the first position and there's a Z here.
What about S2?
Commute.
S3?
Anti.
And S4?
Commute.
And of course, S5 also commutes.
So let's write down the little table of syndromes.
X1, da da da.
1, 0, 1, 0, 0.
Say this is B1, B2, B3, B4, B5.
Now, something nice happens.
I don't need to look over there anymore
because of the cyclic symmetry.
So I want to figure out X2, X3, X4, X5.
I just know what all those rows are.
I just rotate.
So this next one is--
X2 is 0, 1, 0, 1, 0.
X3, I rotate again.
X4, keep rotating.
Et cetera.
Did I get that right?
No.
OK?
So once I know the X1 row, I know all the others,
because they're just related by cyclic shifts.
Any questions about this?
OK.
What about the Z1?
So here, commute, commute, commute, anti, anti.
Right?
So let's go over here and write it down.
0, 0, 0, 1, 1.
And then if you go to the other Z's, you're
just going to cyclically shift this again.
0, 1, 1.
So these are all of the patterns you
can get from a single Z error.
And we're almost done.
The other areas we have to consider are the single qubit
Y's.
Again, I don't want to go back and look at that board.
So how can I calculate the row for Y1?
I heard an answer but it's-- yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
That's right.
So up to a phase, Y is a product of X and Z.
And that phase does not change the commuting,
anti-commuting properties.
So I can just add together the top row here
and the top row here.
And so I get 1, 0, 1, 1, 1.
And then I get all the cyclic shifts of this.
1, 1, 0, 1, 1.
Et cetera.
So now I have these patterns of syndromes.
And I claim that they're all distinct.
And there's no fancy proof.
It's just, you know, there's only 16 of them.
And you can tell they're all different.
The X's, there's two ones with a zero in the middle.
The Z's, there are two ones next to each other,
and the Y's, they're four ones.
I think if you didn't have the fifth column, all of this
would be a little less obvious.
But with the fifth column it makes the argument
a little bit more obvious.
So I've proved my claim that different errors give you
distinct, and not only distinct, but all nonzero B's.
Syndrome vector is B.
So why do I care about this?
The reason is-- let's go back to the quantum error-correcting
conditions.
So we want is that if Psi is in the code space, then Psi EB
dagger EA Psi--
well actually, let me--
sorry.
Let me do it a different way.
So why care about the syndrome?
So the first argument is a little more operational,
which is, given B, we can correct the error.
So suppose what happens is, an unknown poly
happens to our code.
This gives us a recipe for correcting it
because that poly is unitary.
So if we knew what the poly was, we could undo that unitary
and recover our information.
The only problem is, we don't know what it is.
So for example, in the depolarizing channel, an I,
X, Y or Z gets randomly applied.
If you don't know what that is, you
don't know how to correct it.
But this gives us a way to figure out exactly what it is.
You just measure these stabilizers,
look up in these little tables which pattern
your syndrome corresponds to, and then that
will tell you exactly which poly happened.
Then that poly is just unitary.
You can apply another unitary to undo it.
And so this says, in other words,
there exists a recovery map.
So I think that's the simplest argument why
this is sufficient.
And by the way, one of the possible errors
is no error, right?
And that corresponds to the all zero string.
And so it's reassuring that that's
distinct from all the other ones.
If there was some error that looks the same as no error,
then we might potentially be in trouble.
But that's not actually the case.
Every single qubit error is distinguishable
from each other, but also distinguishable from no error
at all.
The second argument is, in terms of the quantum error-correcting
conditions.
So we said that if Psi 1, Psi 2 are orthogonal,
then Psi 1 E1 dagger, E2, Psi 2 should also be orthogonal.
And the reason why they are orthogonal
is because these lead to distinct eigenspaces of S1
through S4.
The fact that the measurements come out differently
means that E2 will send you into one eigenspace--
simultaneous eigenspace of S1, S2, S3, S4.
E1 will send you into a different one.
And we know that distinct eigenspaces
of Hermitian matrices are orthogonal.
And so that means that this vector and that vector
have to be orthogonal to each other.
Unless, of course, E2 and E1 are the same poly, exactly.
And then this cancels out.
And we use the fact that the states
were originally orthogonal.
So one way or another, we get that the final states