In 8.371, we're going to talk about how to think about noise.
So noise is fundamental for classical and quantum
computing.
If your cell phone sends a message to the cell tower,
then your cell phone is using error correcting codes
to protect the information.
For quantum computing, this is an even more necessary part
of building a quantum computer.
The reason why after quantum computers were proposed
and people have been working on it in the lab for a long time,
we still don't have them is because
of the difficulty of contending with noise and quantum systems.
So this is a central part of building
a quantum computer is dealing with noise,
and what you can do with quantum error
correcting codes also connects to many other interesting
fields, such as topological order in condensed matter
systems, understanding quantum key distribution,
a number of things where the connection is not
at all immediately obvious.
So we will talk about error correction in greater detail,
and fault tolerance, fault tolerant quantum computing.
We will also study quantum complexity theory,
which is the study of which problems
are amenable to quantum speed up, and which problems are not.
One particular topic, which is becoming experimentally
relevant today which we'll cover,
is quantum supremacy, which is the goal of building a quantum
computer that can do something that no classical computer can,
and in a sense this is always the goal of quantum computing.
Quantum supremacy focuses on achieving this
with a circuit that may not be useful for anything else.
It's sort of the very first bar that a post classical computer
can achieve.
And complexity theory lets you achieve
this in a way that is, I think, rather surprising.
It let's make a somewhat indirect argument about why
some very near-term quantum circuits cannot be simulated.
So we'll talk about that next.
We'll talk about more advanced quantum algorithms.
So we'll talk about quantum walks, Hamiltonian simulation,
linear system of equations, and other quantum algorithms.
And finally, we'll talk about quantum information theory.
And so many of the breakthroughs of classical information
theory from Shannon, such as using entropy
to describe compression, and noisy channel coding,
all have quantum analogs, and these
are useful not only for dealing with quantum noise,
but also have connections to things like condensed matter
theory, understanding the holographic principle
for black holes.
There's increasingly wide ranging applications
of quantum information theory, which I will briefly allude to,
but mostly I'll give you the foundations of this field