Let me talk about the Stinespring representation
of channels.
By the way, I'm writing operations,
but I'm saying channels.
I mix these up in my head because we often
talk about a quantum channel as something that
takes an input in one place and maps it
as an output to somewhere else.
It's exactly the same thing as a quantum operation.
The two words that mean the same thing.
So one way of thinking about quantum operations
is to go back to the Schrodinger equation.
And the Schrondinger equation says
that all dynamics in the universe are unitary.
So physical dynamics are unitary.
In other words, if you have a state psi, it evolves to U psi
If you have the outer product of psi with itself,
the ket evolves with the U acting on it
at the left, the bra with a dagger on the right.
So a density matrix in general evolves like this.
So this is what the Schrodinger equation says.
It's a crucial feature of quantum theory
that it does not destroy information.
There is now-- or create information.
The amount of information is preserved.
There are people searching for maybe exceptions
to this that might arise with general relativity
in black holes.
But in general, in ordinary circumstances,
we think that quantum mechanics does not create or destroy
information.
So this looks like the end of the story.
That's what we have for pure states.
Maybe it should be the same for density matrices.
But when you're working with physical systems in the lab,
or in trying to build a quantum computer,
we observe things all the time that do not look unitary.
And the reason is, this is true for a closed system.
But we often bring in a new system
that we haven't previously been considering,
or we throw away part of the system
that we had been looking at.
So if we add a system, this looks
like tensoring on a new state.
Or if we discard a subsystem, let's say
our original state was defined on systems A and B,
then we perform the partial trace
and discard one of the subsystems.
We can write this as rho A. And if you
haven't seen the explicit formula for this,
it involves applying the trace map just
to the second of the two systems.
So we could write this as sum over
a basis for system B of identity on A, tensor ket B on system B,
row AB identity on system A. Sorry, this is bra B
and this is ket B on system B. So this
corresponds to discarding one of two systems.
Another way we can write it is as the identity map
on system A, tensor the trace map on system B.
So these are all ways of describing
what happens when we have a composite system
and we throw away part of it.
Just a note about the formalism.
When I write-- these maps I'm considering are in general maps
from density matrices to density matrices.
So I'll define a little bit of notation.
So let's say that A and B are vector spaces.
These are where the states live.
Let me define L of A, L of B to be linear operators on A or B.
So these are linear operators or matrices on these systems.
So a density matrix would live in this space L of A or L of B.
And what we're looking at are maps that take density matrices
to other density matrices.
So you could view these-- actually,
I'll define one more thing.
So L of A, B is linear operators from A to B.
And so if we define L of L of A, L of B,
that means linear operators from L of A to L of B.
So you take in a matrix on system A,
and you output a matrix on system B.
These are sometimes called superoperators, a physics
versus math perspective.
The math perspective is these are all just operators.
They just operate on different vector spaces.
A more physicist way of saying it
is that you have vectors, and then operators,
and then superoperators, and there's more of a hierarchy.
They're both valid ways of thinking about it
that you will encounter in different settings.
So with the partial traces is a linear map
from density matrices on A tensor B
to density matrices only on system A.
So the input is a density matrix on systems A and B,
the output is a density matrix just on system B.
So hopefully, that makes all these equations--
makes it clear what systems we're acting on.
And so in this final line here, when
I write identity sub-A what I mean
is the identity superoperator, the identity that
takes a matrix on system A and spits out
the same matrix on system A.
What about the trace map on system B?
So the input of this is L of B, operators,
matrices on system B. What is the output--
what space is in the output of the trace map?
I heard some-- yeah?
Complex numbers?
Complex numbers.
Exactly.
So the trace takes a matrix here on system B
and spits out just a complex number.
And so I don't write L of A tensor product complex numbers,
because tensoring on just a one-dimensional space
doesn't do anything.
But that's effectively what I have here.
And so we have this part leaves A alone.