I want to be a little bit more clear about errors
being correctable because this condition is a little bit
hard to check, right?
You might worry that in a classical code
it's pretty easy to check whether errors are correctable,
especially these low-weight errors.
I can just check how close are two code words.
And we saw on the classical case that
gave us a precise characterization of up to what
weight of errors I can correct.
Here, the only definition I've given
you is one where you have to come up with a decoding
map yourself.
And so at that point, by the time
you can come up with the decoding map you probably
already have a pretty good understanding of how
the code works.
So is there some more simple characterization we can give
of when the decoding map exists other
than it exists when you can find it and it works?
So that's what I want to talk about.
Now, these are called the quantum error correction
conditions.
And remember in the classical case
the conditions were basically if I have
some set of allowed errors--
let's say I flip up to l bits--
if I can map two codewords to the same points,
then I'm toast.
I cannot correct that error.
If I cannot map two codewords to the same place, I'm happy.
I can correct the errors.
So that's basically what will happen in the quantum case.
We just happen to be a little careful because these are now
vectors and not points.
So we say that s is correctable, or let me let me rephrase that.
Code c corrects a set of errors s if and only if for any pair
of codewords and for any pair of errors they cannot be mapped
not only to the same point--
oh, sorry.
And let me start by demanding that code words be
orthogonal so they're perfectly distinguishable.
Then these errors should not only not
map them to the same point, they shouldn't even ruin their
they're orthogonality.
They shouldn't even map them to nonorthogonal vectors.
So if I have psi 1 and psi 2 like these, and e1 and e2
to are errors, states are orthogonal,
they should remain orthogonal after the errors strike.
So in other words, so this state is what psi 1 gets mapped to.
This is the bra of what psi 2 gets mapped to.
Those states should remain orthogonal.
I'm calling them states, by the way.
They could be sub-normalized, right?
These don't have to be unit vectors.
But whatever states they're proportional to
should be orthogonal.
OK it's just a quantum analog of--
if I'm perfectly distinguishable before,
I should remain perfectly distinguishable
after correctable noise.
I'm making it sound intuitive, but this is a deeply
non-trivial statement.
And I'm not going to prove it because a proof takes a while
and it was in 8370.
And I think you can understand codes
without knowing the proof.
But the proof is also an important thing to know.
So if you didn't take 8370 last year,
I would encourage that you look at the video from last year
and/or read the corresponding parts of Nielsen and Chuang,
which gives the proof of this.
So proof in 8370 or Nielsen and Chuang.
However, I'm not going to reference the proof
on problem sets.
It's not a thing we will directly make use of.
It uses the polar decomposition, some nice facts
about linear algebra.
But yeah.
I will not get into the proof further.
I do want to give one equivalent way of thinking about this,
which maybe gives you a first step
in the direction of the proof.
I should say, what I mean by correct a set of errors
is there exists a decoding map that works, OK?
I should say this.
So correct means there exists decoding and recovery
maps that perfectly recover the original information, OK?
So what's nice about this condition
is that you can state it without any reference to decoding map.
Maybe it's not easy to check always.
That may or may not be true.
But you don't need to come up with a decoding map
in order to check this.
If the condition is satisfied, you know such a map exists.
And in fact, the proof even gives you
a prescription for finding it.
So actually, there is one more thing
I want to say about these conditions, which is a little
bit subtle, which is, people often
talk about a code in saying oh, this error is
correctable by the code, and that error is not
corrected by the code.
And that is a dangerous way of thinking.
So suppose there's some error that
seems very hard to correct, like I flipped 17 qubits with x's
and I apply a bunch of z's to other qubits.
If it's any single unitary error,
if I knew what the error was, I could correct it, right?
The issue is really dealing with sets of errors.
So whenever I just say a code, correct something,
I'm always saying it corrects a set of possible errors.
And that's because if I knew what the particular error was,
I could tailor the decoding map to that,
and that would be cheating.
The decoding map has to work precisely
because I don't know what the error is.
And so that's why the order of quantifiers is,
I achieve my code first.
Then there's some set of errors.
And then I choose the decoding map
based on that set of errors.
And then I'm handed one particular realization
of errors from that set, and by decoding map has to handle it.
So as we go on, just remember that we talk about
whether a set of errors is correctable.
We might be sloppy and say, does this error lie
within the decorrectable set or not.
But that's only after we've already fixed
a particular correctable set.