OK, so what kinds of matrices can be density matrices?
A density matrix is trace 1 positive semidefinite
and Hermitian.
And, in, fact all Hermitian positive semidefinite trace 1
matrices are density matrices.
So summation p's of i, psi of i, psi of i, tracing this.
This matrix, psi i, psi i, has trace 1
because the normal psi is 1.
So this is equal to sum p of i trace psi i, psi
i equals sum pi equals 1.
OK, positive semidefinite.
OK, so here you need to know something
about positive semidefinite matrices, which
I don't know if I have proved, but I'm not going to.
I'm just going to tell you.
So if you have two positives semidefinite matrices
and you add them, you get another positive semidefinite
matrix.
So positive semidefinite permission
means all eigenvalues are greater than or equal to 0.
So this matrix has one eigenvalue of 1
and all the rest are 0, and the eigenvalue
is, of course, psi of i.
So it's positive semidefinite.
So its sum, and you're adding a bunch of them--
so the sum is also positive semidefinite.
It's Hermitian, which means its conjugate is
its transpose, because each of these is Hermitian.
So we've shown that any density matrix
is trace 1 positive semidefinite permission.
But the other way around holds as well.
If m is Hermitian, then m is equal to summation lambda i
equals 1 through d, lambda i vi vi, where the v's of i
are eigenvectors.
First, all the vi's are perpendicular,
so you can easily see that vi is an eigenvalue of this matrix
with--
eigenvalue of lambda i.
And, in fact, that's the unique matrix,
which has eigenvectors v's of i with eigenvalues lambda i.
Eigenvalues.
So a matrix is a density matrix if, and only if, it's
positive semidefinite permission trace 1.