Before I go on, I want to justify this claim
that every stabilizer cuts down the dimension by a half.
And to do that, we will calculate the projector
onto a code subspace.
So let me talk about stabilizer--
subspace-- projectors.
So-- let me define pi sub s--
to be the projector onto to V sub s.
Should I explain what I mean by a projector onto a subspace?
It just means a linear operator that maps everything
into the subspace.
And then if you're already in the subspace,
it acts trivially.
So you can think of it as Hermitian operator
It's plus 1 eigenspace corresponding to this subspace.
And everything else is a 0 eigenspace, OK?
So we want to know how to calculate this object.
And-- I claim there's a nice formula for it--
which is given by taking your stabilizer subgroup
and just averaging over it.
So this is the number of elements in the stabilizer
subgroup.
You divide by that.
And then you sum over all the elements--
just put that matrix there.
So if I average over the stabililzer subgroup,
I claim this gives me a projector onto the code
subspace.
And this fact, by the way, is sort of a general math fact.
This does not rely on any properties of the polys.
It just relies on that top definition up there a,
Vs. And on the fact that s is a group.
So-- let me sketch the proof of this.
So the first thing I want to observe is that if g is in s--
then g times pi s is equal to pi s.
OK, so why is this true?
Well, if you look at g pi s, I can think of this as sum
over the elements of the group--
g times h.
Will let me divide--
let me put the normalization factor over here--
so I don't have to keep writing it.
So I get sum over the elements of the group, g times h.
And now-- the key thing about a group
is that because it's closed under multiplication
and has inverses, it's got some list of elements.
And if I take each one of those elements
and multiply it by an element of the group,
it sends each element to a different element in the group.
Maybe the same but some other element.
And this mapping must be one to one
This multiplication will never send
two elements to the same one.
Because if it did, things would not be invertible.
If it did, I couldn't invert left multiplication
if this left multiplication was destroying information
by sending two elements to the same one.
So when I take the list of elements in s
and multiply each one on the left by g,
I have to just get back the elements of s
in some other order.
So this must be sum over h prime in s.
you can call h prime, gh, if you like of h prime.
Yeah.
How do I know the pi system?
Yes, yes, you're absolutely right.
Let me do this.
Let me define pi s to be this sum right here.
And then I claim it's equal to the projector.
So, right, so the objection is I defined
pi s to be the projector onto the subspace.
And I claimed it had this form.
Of, course, in the end, we'll see that they're all equal.
But the way I want to do the proof is in the other order.
I want to start by defining pi s to be
this average over the elements of the stabilizer
through just some mathematical object.
I have no idea if it's a projector yet.
And I will prove to you that it is in fact the desired
projector.
OK?
So pi s is this object.
And it has the property that if I multiply on the left by g--
I get back this object.
OK?
Because now I have this sum over h prime
which is just the reordering of the elements in s.
So that proves this fact that if I
multiply pi s on the left by g, I get back pi s.
Now you're absolutely right.
We have no idea what pi s is.
Other than the sum, we just know one property of it.
So what do we do with this fact?
So what that implies--
is-- if g is in s--
G dagger is in s.
And so G dagger pi s is also equal to pi s--
right.
G is closed under inverses.
These elements are all unitary.
And so in particular, if I have one G dagger
and multiply on the left by pi s.
If I average over a bunch of them, the same thing is true.
So in particular, pi s dagger times pi s is equal to pi s.
So I've just replaced the G dagger here
with an average over all of the G daggers.
In other words, with pi s dagger.
OK?
Now this last equation tells us that pi s is a projector.
So why is that?
Well, if you're of this form, you must be Hermitian.
In fact, you must be positive semidefinite.
In fact, all of your eigenvalues should have the property
that when you square them, you get back the same eigenvalue.
Now what numbers squared equal themselves?
The only options are 0 and 1.
So from this equation, you know that all
of the eigenvalues of pi s are 0 and 1 and that it's Hermitian.
So that means it's a projector onto something.
The only debate now is what does it project onto?
Does it, in fact, project onto V sub s?
OK?
So therefore, the eigenvalues of pi s are all 0, 1.
So the only question is what does this project onto?
So let's suppose you have pi s times some arbitrary state, Cy.
And we multiply by g for sum.
So g is in s.
Cy Is arbitrary.
What can we say about this equation--
about this expression?
What does that equal to?
Yeah?
You're pointing--
[INAUDIBLE]
Right, you're saying it satisfies the stabilizer
equation.
It's unaffected by g.
So we know that g times pi s is equal to pi s.
So this is equal to pi s Cy.
So if you put parentheses here, this vector is stabilized by g.
So therefore, pi s Cy is in Vs. In other words, the image of pi
s is contained in Vs On the other hand,
if Cy already belongs to Vs, then
all of the g's act trivially.
So then-- when we apply pi s to it,
all these g's just act like identity.
And so we get back Cy.
So this means that Vs is contained in the image of pi s.
So finally, we have that pi s projects onto a projector.
And its image is exactly equal to the space that we want.
So, therefore, pi s is equal to the projector
onto Vs. Any questions about this argument?
Yeah.
Can you explain why is dagger into the s?
Why G dagger's an s?
S is a group, so it contains its inverses.
And the elements of s are all unitary.
So their inverses are just given by their daggers.
[INAUDIBLE]
That's right.
Yeah, nothing in my argument used the fact
that s was a polygroup.
This is a totally general fact about groups.
Why is g [INAUDIBLE]
OK, so I guess I don't want to address the general group
situation.
There's one thing I'm sort of conflating which
is the elements of a group with some unitary representation
of them.
So, really, what I should say is this works
for any subgroup of unitaries.
Good.
Any other questions?
OK, so why did we do this?
I mean, it's nice to have a deal with a calculate projector.
Here's one immediate thing we get from this.
So-- let's try to calculate the dimension of the stabilizer
subspace.
If you look at that definition up there,
it looks pretty complicated, right.
It depends on the intersection of all these
plus 1 eigenspaces.
Who knows how they intersect.
It was what I said before.
Do they always have to cut each other in half or not?
But now that I have a formula for the projector,
I can just say, this is equal to the trace of the projector.
Because the trace if it's 0's and 1's, this will just count
the number of 1's-- the number of dimensions.
And trace is linear, so this is just average over s--
sum over g and s--
trace g.
So-- now-- this seems a little tough
because s is a general group.
But what can I say about the trace of a polymatrix?
It's 0-- mostly 0.
When is it not 0?
The identity.
So the only time it's non 0 is if it's the identity.
So if this giant sum--
but we don't care about most of it.
We only care about a single term which
is the identity, which has trace 2 to the n.
So this whole thing--
is 2 to the n over the size of the stabilizer group.